<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Philosophy | Harvey Xia]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//blog/categories/philosophy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//"/>
  <updated>2015-07-27T19:24:32-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harvey Xia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harvey@harveyxia.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Morality: A Necessary Component of Rationality]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//morality-a-necessary-component-of-rationality"/>
    <updated>2013-05-03T23:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//morality-a-necessary-component-of-rationality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why be moral? It’s a question that keeps philosophers up at night, perhaps even more so than questions about what morality demands. This question is difficult to answer because of the seemingly contradictory natures of morality and rationality. It seems fair to say that, regardless of its particular principles, a plausible moral theory must demand self-sacrifice of individuals. This is simply obvious. It also seems intuitive that the proper account of rationality is one that is based on self-interest. That is to say, the reasons that motivate us are ones that accord with our self-interest. This claim is more controversial and many philosophers argue that it is the wrong account of rationality. I hope to defend the account of rationality as founded on self-interest, and to offer the beginnings of a possible answer to the question “Why be moral?” within the framework that this account of rationality entails. To illustrate my point most effectively, I will argue the latter claim before the former.</p>

<p>First, let’s just assume that our rationality is based predominantly on our self-interest. How do we reconcile morality’s demand of self-sacrifice and rationality’s demand of self-interest? One might be inclined to give the Big Stick Solution (henceforth, BSS): it is rational to be moral because the individual will be punished if he cheats the moral system. Since it is not in his self-interest to be punished, he must adhere to the moral system. This solution relies on the assumption that there exists an omniscient and omnipotent enforcer who has the power to both perfectly know and punish those who cheat the system. The legal system of a society might be such an enforcer. For instance, society punishes individuals who commit murder by taking their freedom taken away and placing them in prison. Even ignoring practical questions of the possibility of an adequate enforcement, there is a significant problem with this approach: it subordinates morality to self-interest and defines self-interest in terms of personal well-being. The solution suggests that morality should only be valued insofar as it affects our personal well-being. People shouldn’t commit murder because they will get caught and punished. This account of morality seems obviously false because morality should be valued in and of itself. In other words, morality should considered as an end, not simply as a means to promoting our well being. Given that the BSS relies on an account of morality that is so implausible, it does not give us the best answer for the question “Why be moral?”</p>

<p>The BSS also employs the wrong account of human rationality for two reasons. The first reason is that it defines our self-interest negatively by claiming that humans desire not to be punished. It is insufficient to portray our rationality in terms of what we want to avoid. Of course we want to avoid physical and emotional harm, but our rationality strives for more than just ensuring our safety against what we fear. I acknowledge that nevertheless, avoiding harm is indeed a goal of rationality. But in answering the question, “Why be moral”, we must look at the complete account of rationality. Morality does not only relate to rationality through the one desire to avoid punishment. Our rationality gives us both long and short term ends that we pursue in order to better our lives. It seems better to define our rationality positively, in terms of striving to live the best life possible and fulfilling the goals that rationality determines. Thus, in discussing the relationship between morality and rationality, morality does not simply matter insofar as the failure to obey its rules might bring us harm. To give a satisfying account of why acting morally is also acting rationally, morality must be discussed as it pertains to fulfilling the goals that our rationality sets.</p>

<p>As I mentioned before, the BSS makes the mistake of defining self-interest solely in terms of well-being. For the BSS theorist, what’s in our self-interest is what promotes our own well-being. Thus, the problem of treating morality merely a means arises because this view commits the BSS theorist to value morality only insofar as morality affects well-being. But self-interest is clearly not the same as well-being. An action can promote my self-interest but be harmful to my well-being. Conversely, something can promote my well-being without promoting my self-interest. For instance, I can choose to donate one of my kidneys to my brother. This would be in my self-interest because I care about my brother’s health, but it would not be promoting my well-being because I am giving away my organ. The concept of self-interest can be explained more coherently by basing it on rational desires. A rational desire is a desire that is based on the reasons available to the individual at that time. A psychopathic desire to murder people is not a rational desire. A desire to donate one’s kidney to save a family member is a rational desire. What’s in my self-interest is what fulfills my rational desires.</p>

<p>If it is in one’s self-interest to act according to their rational desires, then a simpler solution to the moral question emerges. Why be moral? Because we have the rational desire to be moral, and it is in our rational self-interest to fulfill these desires. One’s first impression might be that this solution is circular: we should be moral because we should be moral. But this is misunderstanding the logic; we should be moral because we rationally want to be moral. Of course it could be objected that not everybody has the rational desire to be moral, that some people abhor morality and consciously act against its principles. Recall, however, that the BSS was inadequate because it treated morality as a means rather than an end. This was enough for us to reject the BSS because intuitively, we believe that obeying morality has intrinsic value. This very intuition shows us that most of us have the desire to be moral, regardless of what the content of the moral system are. Insofar as we have the rational desire to be moral and that to act rationally with regard to our self-interest means to act in way that promotes the realization of these rational desires, we should be moral. This solution offers a way to reconcile the seemingly contrary demands of morality and of rationality, while allowing us to preserve the self-interested account of rationality.</p>

<p>What about the individual who has no desire to be moral? It seems unlikely that we can both maintain our notion of morality as having intrinsic value and find reasons that motivate him to be moral. If he does not have the desire to be moral, then acting morally for the sake of acting morally cannot be in his self-interest. For such a person, it seems that the best we can do is to revert back to the BSS, and treat morality as a means for promoting his other self-interests, most of which perhaps connect with his well-being. This way, at least we can convince him to carry out the moral actions even though he will be doing them for the wrong reasons (through purely selfish motivations).</p>

<p>Now I turn to the question of our rationality. What is the correct account of human rationality? Someone might look at the simple solution I proposed and object that it is unlikely that human self-interests include the desire to promote the well-being of others. After all, the rational interests in question are self-interests, not others’¬-interests. But this is to confuse self-interest with selfishness. As I explained above, what’s in one’s self-interest does not simply consist of what promotes one’s own well-being. Similarly, what’s in one’s self-interest does not simply consist of selfish desires. It can very well be in one’s self-interest to devote the greater part of his life to raising and caring for his children, even though doing so would involve sacrificing a significant amount of his own time, energy, and money. Self-sacrifice for others can be, and often is, an essential aspect of one’s self-interest.</p>

<p>Again, skeptics of this account of rationality might say, “By this account, the only thing I want is what’s in my self-interest. This is just obviously wrong.” But this is not the self-interested account of rationality that I put forth. The account I put forth claims that the only thing in one’s self-interest is what one wants. That is, what one’s self-interest consists of is necessarily and sufficiently explained by what one wants, which consist of the reasons one has to want something. This is the correct way to understand the self-interested account of rationality.</p>

<p>The best objection one might raise to the arguments I’ve put forth is that, “Surely the moral desire is only one of many conflicting desires an individual possesses at any point in time. Why should he choose to follow the moral desire rather than other, perhaps more selfish, desires?” This objection would be relevant for other accounts of rationality as well. If what’s rational is determined both by selfish concerns for one’s own well-being and altruistic concerns for the well-being of others, there will be conflicting desires. Why should the individual choose to act with regard to the self-interest of others over his own? Why should the individual choose to follow his moral desire? Regardless of what theory of rationality we believe, further arguments must be made to show why it is rational that the moral desire should take precedence over other desires. This is the great difficulty of moral philosophy, to construct an argument defending this normative claim and to show the validity of its normative force.</p>

<p>I did not discuss this question here, and by no means do I pretend to have fully answered the initial question, “Why be moral?” But I hope I have shown how such an answer is possible given the self-interested account of rationality, and why such an account of rationality is plausible. Unlike the Big Stick Solution, my argument does not rely on the existence of an omnipotent and omniscient enforcer. My argument relies only on the reasonable assumption that people have the desire to be moral. And from this we can see that it is rational to be moral because we have the desire to do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Insufficiency of Kant’s Universal Law Formulation]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-insufficiency-of-kants-universal-law-formulation"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T12:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-insufficiency-of-kants-universal-law-formulation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Universal Law Formulation of Kant’s Categorical Imperative states, “Act only on that maxim through which you can at the same time will that it should become a universal law” (88). Regarding the nature of the ULF Kant asserts, “…there remains nothing over to which the maxim has to conform except the universality of a law as such; and it is this conformity alone that the imperative properly asserts to be necessary” (88). Here Kant makes explicit the idea his ethical system uses universability through reason as the single necessary and sufficient condition for moral evaluation. If a maxim (a general ethical principle put into first-person terms) can be rationally willed by the individual to be universalized and shared by every rational being in the world, then the maxim and its related action are morally permissible. I will argue that universability through reason alone does not provide sufficient conditions for evaluating the morality of maxims by showing how the proper application of ULF can yield two conflicting morally obligatory answers. By morally obligatory (and I will illustrate this concept in more detail below), I mean an action that must be carried out and for which it is immoral not to. If such is possible, Kant’s moral theory is shown to be inadequate because a plausible moral theory must give non-conflicting answers.</p>

<p>Under Kant’s moral system, evaluating the morality of an action involves subjecting it to this test of universability, which I will call the ULF test. A maxim can fail the test in two ways: it can give rise to a contradiction in conception or a contradiction in willing. Contradiction in conception occurs when it is impossible to even conceive of a world in which the given maxim is universalized. Contradiction in willing occurs when the individual finds himself worse off in a where the given maxim is universalized, and so cannot will it to be universal. For a maxim to pass the test, it must have neither contradiction. For an action to be morally permissible, its maxim must pass the test. For an action to be morally obligatory, all the maxims permitting the failure of carrying out that action must fail the ULF test. Conversely, for an action to be morally forbidden, all the maxims permitting that action must fail.</p>

<p>Consider the following scenario: a paramedic on the scene of a car accident. The car drove off a bridge and fell into a river. The driver of the car could not escape the car and drowned. Upon examining the body, the paramedic concludes that the driver did not die instantly, but drowned while struggling desperately to escape. When the driver’s wife arrives on the scene of the accident, she asks the paramedic if her husband died quickly or suffered before his death. What should the paramedic tell her?</p>

<p>The ULF test can yield the answer that it is morally obligatory to tell the wife the truth. Every maxim that permits lying to the wife contradicts itself in conception because in a world where every paramedic simply told the story that is easier for the wife to bear (that the victim died painlessly), there would be no point to even asking the paramedic in the first place. In such a world, the victim’s wife would know that the paramedic always gives this answer, regardless of the truth, so they would see no point in asking. Furthermore, there seems to be a contradiction in willing for maxims which permit lying in these cases. Could the paramedic really will that all paramedics in this position lie? Then, if the paramedic were to find himself in the position of the wife, he would never know the truth about the victim’s death. Surely he cannot will that he himself might be placed in such an undesirable situation. On the other hand, maxims that permit telling the truth all pass the ULF test. There is no contradiction in conception because wives would continue to ask paramedics for the true account of how the victim died. There is no contradiction in will because if the paramedic were placed in such a situation, he would want to know that the story the paramedic tells him is in fact true. The honest paramedic would argue that it is morally obligatory to tell the truth because all maxims permitting lying in this scenario would fail because they rise to both contradictions in conception and will.</p>

<p>However, the ULF test can also yield the answer that it is morally obligatory to lie to the wife. In response to the arguments above that a lie-permitting maxim would generate a contradiction in conception, the dishonest paramedic could argue that such a contradiction only arises if the paramedic’s sole duty is to tell the truth. He might argue that while telling the truth is one possible purpose, the greater purpose is to lessen the emotional trauma of the victim’s wife. If this latter purpose has been established as a premise, then there is no contradiction in conception because the paramedic would still have a purpose answering the wife, which is to reduce her emotional suffering. While the honest paramedic might rebut by pointing out that in a world where this maxim is universalized, the wife would know that the paramedic only ever gives the easier account, and so their emotional trauma would not be lessened because they would still left in uncertainty about what happened. But even so, for the wife, there still exists a 50% chance that her husband actually died painlessly according to the paramedic. If the paramedic always told the truth, then the wife either knows 100% that the husband died painfully or painlessly. By eliminating the possibility that the wife knows for certain her husband died painfully, the wife is better off emotionally. This is resting on the assumption that, for anyone in the wife’s situation, the emotional suffering that would occur from knowing the worse outcome greatly outbalances the peace of mind from knowing the better outcome. As for contradiction in willing, the dishonest paramedic agrees with the above assumption and would rather be left uncertain than chance knowing the worse outcome. Thus, the dishonest paramedic can reasonably will this maxim to be universal. More importantly, he would argue that giving the easier account is morally obligatory because all maxims permitting the paramedic to tell the truth in the case where the victim died painfully would fail the ULF test. Given that the duty of the paramedic is to reduce the emotional trauma of the already suffering wife, he must give the easier answer. A contradiction in willing arises otherwise, because the honest paramedic could not will himself to be in a situation where he is at danger for suffering the additional emotional weight of knowing the victim died painfully.</p>

<p>The ULF test seems to yield two conflicting answers, that it is morally obligatory to tell the truth and that it is morally obligatory to lie and give the easier answer. Why do the two paramedics reach opposite conclusions while properly applying the ULF test?</p>

<p>This problem, as I see it, arises because the ULF does not contain enough content to yield clear and non-conflicting moral answers. Because both views are supported by reason and both pass the ULF test as obligatory, universability through reason is shown to be insufficient to yield a single moral answer, and thus insufficient as the sole condition of an ethical system. There is a missing ingredient that differentiates why an individual would choose one position over the other. The issue is put into focus in examining how each side argues that the other side leads to contradictions in willing. The honest paramedic believes that no rational individual in this situation would will themselves into a position where he would be lied to, while the dishonest paramedic believes that no rational individual in this position would will themselves into a more emotionally vulnerable position. It seems that the two paramedics value different things in this situation: the honest paramedic values knowing the truth and the dishonest paramedic values peace of mind. It is the paramedics’ different values that cause them to make opposite conclusions. A plausible moral theory must include a mechanism that allows the individual to establish the relative importance of values in any given moral dilemma. As illustrated by the paramedic example, mere universability fails to do this. It seems perfectly reasonable to me that an individual can will a world where everybody in the paramedic scenario values knowing the truth, or that he wills a world where everybody values avoiding further emotional stress. Both of these values can be universalized through reason.</p>

<p>The Kantian might contend reason is sufficient to determine what values are most important. He might argue that truth is obviously more valuable than emotional comfort because the successful function of rationality depends on understanding of the truth. Because rationality guides our actions and helps us make the best decisions, it is in everybody’s best interest to maximize the access they have to reality. While this argument might hold true if we are talking about the scope of one’s lifetime, it does not, I think, hold for the isolated paramedic case. If I stipulate that the wife’s knowing or not knowing the truth is inconsequential with respect to her future rational decisions, then the argument that truth is more valuable falls apart. I acknowledge that I have sketched a consequentialist argument for the value of truth and that there are other ways of arguing for truth’s value. However, I think the consequentialist argument for truth is the strongest insofar as we are discussing the application of the ULF because it is most likely to be universalized. It is harder to universalize a value based on a belief in its intrinsic importance, because other individuals might not share that belief. The Kantian might still argue that the perfect use of reason is sufficient to yield this hierarchy of values. But since I have never seen this successfully demonstrated, I remain unconvinced. It seems then, that the application of reason alone leaves room for valuing both truth and emotional comfort, but provides no way of choosing between the two. Keep in mind that one of the two values must take precedence in this case of two conflicting morally obligatory answers in which the ULF has been applied properly in both positions.</p>

<p>It would be beyond the scope of this paper to introduce a plausible mechanism for deciding the relative importance of values in cases like these. I hope I have shown that Kant’s ULF, which contains universability through reason as its only condition for moral evaluation, is insufficient. In conceiving of the ULF, Kant seems to have overextended the powers of reason far beyond what is plausible for an ethical theory. Although I realize that a discussion about the nature of reason itself would require much detail than what I can offer here, I will nevertheless venture to make some remarks about reason as they relate to the shortcomings of Kant’s moral theory. Reason is most effective as an evaluative instrument given the initial premises. It cannot, however, be relied on alone to generate fundamental premises for a moral theory, let alone plausibly universal premises. Even the perfect use of reason cannot do this. Thus, individuals properly applying reason will arrive at different moral conclusions if they have different premises or moral values. The nature of reason is different than what Kant thought, and the ULF must be amended to include a way for individuals with different values to rationally evaluate the importance of their own values relative to other values in a given moral dilemma, with the goal of arriving at a definitive moral answer. Although the question remains open as to whether or not any moral system can fully achieve this goal, Kant’s ULF can without a doubt be improved in this respect.</p>

<p>Works Cited</p>

<p>Kant, Immanuel. Ground of the Metaphysics of Morals. Trans. H.J. Paton. New York: Harper    Perennial, 2009.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assertions: Updating the Context Set]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//assertions-updating-the-context-set"/>
    <updated>2013-04-24T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//assertions-updating-the-context-set</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In his article <a href="http://www.princeton.edu/~harman/Courses/PHI534-2012-13/Lepore/stalnaker78.pdf">“Assertion"</a>, Stalnaker gives a pragmatic account of the function of assertions in language. He states that assertions, when not rejected by other conversational participants, serve to reduce the context set of the conversation. Stalnaker uses the term ‘context set’ to refer to the set of all possible worlds that are compatible with the presuppositions of the speaker. For instance, in a conversation about upcoming weekend plans, the context set cannot include possible worlds where the speaker is talking with the philosopher Kant because such worlds do not accord with the presupposition that Kant is dead. Assertions reduce the context set by taking into account the content represented by the proposition asserted to the existing presuppositions. Increasing the number of things presupposed will necessarily lead to a reduction in the context set because the addition of new presuppositions rules out worlds incompatible with the proposition. For Stalnaker, a proposition is a “representation of the world as being a certain way,” and so determines a set of possible worlds. So another way of thinking about Stalnaker’s account of assertions is that when assertions are made, the intersection of the existing context set and the set of possible worlds represented by the proposition becomes the new context set. I will argue, however, that assertions can also function to broaden the context set. If this is true, then assertions function to update the context set rather than just restricting it, contrary to Stalnaker’s account.</p>

<p>Stalnaker states that he does not offer this account as a sufficient definition of assertion, but rather as one component of an adequate definition. Although he makes some remarks about the reason why assertions cannot be sufficiently defined by this effect alone, he does not mention anything about assertions being able to broaden the context set. It seems to me that such assertions occur regularly, even in “non-nondefective” conversations where the speakers initially presuppose the same things. If assertions can in fact broaden the context, Stalnaker’s account of this particular function of assertions is inadequate.</p>

<p>Suppose two friends are deciding on what type of restaurant to go to. They typically prefer pizza and have only ever been to pizza restaurants. One of them asks, “What pizza place do you want to go to?” On this particular day, however, the other replies, “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place,” and the other agrees. The initial context set only included worlds where the two are eating at pizza restaurants. It seems that the new context set includes worlds where the two are eating at restaurants that both serve pizza and do not (assuming that the speaker did not mean to rule out possible worlds where the two still went to a pizza restaurant).</p>

<p>But there arises a problem. What is semantically expressed by propositions of the form, “It might be that,” or “It could be that,” turns out to be either necessarily true or necessarily false for all the worlds in the context set. The semantic content of “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place” is that there is some world Φ in the context set in which the two are not eating at a pizza place. In the existing context set, there either is a world Φ or there isn’t. If Φ does exist in the context set, then for every possible world in the context set, the proposition is true.  But in the pizza case, since it was presupposed by both speakers that they would eat at a pizza place, the world Φ is not in the context set. Therefore, the statement “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place” is necessarily false relative to every possible world in the context set.</p>

<p>This violates the principle that Stalnaker takes to be a necessary for rational communication: a proposition asserted must be true in some but not all of the possible worlds in the context set. This principle seems obvious because otherwise the proposition expressed would not be advancing the conversation in any way since it is either trivially true or trivially false. If we assume that the speaker is rational and intends on engaging in a genuine conversation, it seems wrong to interpret his statement as asserting a proposition that is trivially false. Something else seems to be happening. Thus, the fact that the statement is trivially false triggers a pragmatic, Gricean reinterpretation. The speaker wishes to communicate something other than what is literally asserted by the utterance. Given that the statement is false at all possible worlds in the context set, it seems that the speaker wishes to broaden the context set to include possible worlds in which the two are not eating at a pizza place. I will explain how this is possible.</p>

<p>If the other speaker agrees, the context set is broadened to now include the world(s) Φ where they are not eating at a pizza place. Consequently, what’s true for the worlds in the context set has changed. Now, there are worlds for which it is possible that the two might eat at a non-pizza place. The new context set is the result of the union of the previous context set and the set of possible worlds represented by the asserted proposition. But once the context set is updated to include world Φ, there remains the problem that now the statement is trivially true. One solution to this problem is that what is possible at each of the possible worlds is different. At some set of worlds in the context set, it is possible that they will eat at a pizza place. At some other set of worlds in the context set, it is possible that they will eat at a non-pizza place. I offer this only as a mere gesture towards what an adequate solution may be. For the purposes of this paper, I assume that such a solution is possible. The exact details of that solution are not critical to my argument.</p>

<p>The statement is no longer trivially false because it accords with the principle that the proposition asserted is true in some but not all of the worlds in the context set. The speaker has successfully advanced the conversation by broadening the context set. This claim runs contrary to Stalnaker’s notion that the new context set is the result of the intersection of the existing context set and the set of worlds represented by the proposition asserted. I see no reason why the context set cannot be changed by either the intersection or the union of itself with an asserted proposition, depending on whether the assertion is intended to restrict or broaden the context set, respectively. It seems more accurate to say that conversations are advanced when the context set is updated in some way, rather than only restricted.</p>

<p>Statements of the form “It might be the case that…” or “It could be the case that…” often signal an assertion that broadens the context set. One might argue that such statements are not assertions, but some other linguistic move that functions differently. These sorts of utterances, however, do seem to be assertions. When he says “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place” he is really asserting the proposition that represents the set of worlds in which the two are eating at a non-pizza restaurant, along with expressing his desire that the other speaker accept this assertion.</p>

<p>Philosophical skeptics often make these statements. If a skeptic utters, “We could be experiencing a dream right now,” he is asserting the proposition that represents the worlds in which the speaker is dreaming. It would be unfair to think that skeptical utterances cannot be assertions; certain types of skeptical utterances, especially philosophical ones, aim expressly to break down certain presuppositions, opening up new possible worlds to consider in the discussion.</p>

<p>To defend this claim of mine, it is important to consider why Stalnaker thinks of assertions as functioning solely to restrict the context set. Stalnaker accounts for assertions in this way because the point of a conversation (or at least, the type of conversation in which assertions are employed) is to locate the actual world that the speakers are in. By restricting the context set and limiting the set of possible worlds as live options, the speakers hope to eventually reach a point where only one possible world remains, that one being the real world. Of course, this is only a brief sketch of what actually happens. Different conversations would require different degrees of certainty; a conversation centered on diagnosing a patient would demand that only a single world be left as a live option, so that the doctors know exactly how to treat him. In a conversation about a sports game between two speakers who don’t particular care about sports, the speakers would be satisfied with a number of possible worlds as live options (“The Celtics won, but the final score was either 98-78 or 99-76”).</p>

<p>Given the goal of locating the actual world within the context set, it very well might be the case that a mistake was made by the speakers and the actual world was ruled out by certain false presuppositions. If, as Stalnaker suggests, the role of assertions is to locate the actual world, then it seems perfectly justified, perhaps even necessary, that assertions also function to broaden the context set in such situations. As mentioned above, Cartesian philosophical skeptics make certain statements to account for the possibility that the world is just an illusion orchestrated by an evil demon. Since they are aiming to uncover a metaphysical truth (attempting to locate the real world within the context set), the skeptics are indeed making assertions.</p>

<p>Perhaps another example will make this point clearer. Consider a murder investigation. Two detectives are examining the crime scene and debating possible suspects given the available evidence. They suspect that either the maid or the wife committed the murder, and so the context set contains the possible worlds where the maid or wife committed the crime. Suddenly one of the detectives receives a phone call from an informant telling him that there is strong evidence implicating the butler. This detective then utters, “The butler could have done it.” It is perfectly reasonable to interpret this statement as asserting the proposition that represents the possible worlds in which the butler committed the murder, thus expanding the context set (because otherwise the assertion would be trivially false, violating one of basic conversational principles regarding assertions). After all, the detectives are there to find out who killed the victim. If evidence arises implicating the butler, it seems logically necessary to expand the context set to include worlds in which the butler is the murderer, if the actual world is to be accurately located.</p>

<p>It is not a justified defense to claim that statements that broaden the context set are not assertions. Statements that broaden the context set have the same purpose that Stalnaker suggests for assertions that reduce the context set — to update the context set in hopes of locating the actual world. If the speaker’s hold a mistaken presupposition and the actual world is not within the current context set, it is necessary to broaden the context set to contain the set possible worlds where the real world might be located. Given that locating the real world is the purpose for making assertions, it is insufficient to account for assertions as only reducing the context set. The essential function of assertions seems to be that they update the context set, both by restricting and by expanding it. </p>

<p>Works Cited</p>

<ol>
<li>Robert Stalnaker, “Assertion,” Syntax and Semantics, ed. J. Kimball. Vol. 9, 1978 Academic   Press (New York), pp. 315-332.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mental State Theory: An Inadequate Picture of Happiness]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness"/>
    <updated>2013-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>In investigating questions of human happiness, it’s important to explore the very concept of happiness itself. Unfortunately, this word is used in myriad contexts and comes loaded with many meanings. For the purposes of this article, I will use the term to refer to the deeper type of happiness that we associate with human flourishing — the type of happiness we mean when we ask ourselves the question, “Am I <em>really</em> happy?”</p>

<p>Questioning this type of happiness itself will hopefully bring into focus a better picture of the nature of happiness and its role in human flourishing, as well as introduce important questions that must be addressed in giving an adequate account of happiness. Though I acknowledge the fact that happiness has an inescapably subjective nature — after all, each of us is made happy by different things — I think we can still hold meaningful discussions about the objective aspects of happiness, namely, what it is that we think happiness <em>consists</em>.</p>

<p>Instead of attempting to answer this question directly (which would require much more than one article), I will dispute the common belief that happiness only consists of mental states, or that to be happy means to be in a certain psychological state. This particular conception of happiness is widespread. Popular moral theories, including many (although not all) variants of Utilitarianism, rest on the idea that what humans desire are positive mental states, or pleasure. Furthermore, it seems to me that in our every day lives, our default intuition seems to support decisions that maximize the pleasure of ourselves or others. It requires deeper reflection to <em>override</em> this default concern for mental states for the sake of some other value. A common example of this is when somebody accepts that they have done something wrong — his initial instinct is not to admit his fault, for that would invoke feelings of shame and guilt. But upon further reflection, he realizes that the better action is to apologize and recognize his fault for whatever reason (so that he can avoid making the same mistake next time, or that he can become a better person, etc.).</p>

<p>In challenging this simple and compelling notion of happiness as purely a psychological state, the philosopher Robert Nozick employed a well-known thought experiment known as “The Experience Machine.” Imagine sometime in the future in which human beings have the technology and the understanding of neurophysiology to construct a machine that can perfectly produce any psychological state. Once plugged in, the individual’s thoughts and beliefs can be altered in any way — he can be made to think that he is the greatest writer in the world, the greatest musician, the most wealthy, the best looking, the most popular, the most well-liked, etc. He can be made to believe, and more importantly <em>feel as if</em>, his life is perfect in every aspect; his days would be filled with nothing but elation and contentment. Assume that, while in the Experience Machine, the individual believes everything he is experiencing is real, i.e., he is not aware of being in an experience machine, and further, has no memory of being plugged in.</p>

<p>Would you plug in? Nozick believed that most people would say no, especially when given enough time to think about it. This intuitive answer does not cohere with the view that happiness is constituted only by mental states. The Experience Machine can give us the best mental states imaginable, so why would we (or at least most of us) turn down the chance to plug in?</p>

<p>A common response in defense of mental state theories is that the thought experiment is too removed from our reality. The thought experiment is too abstract, or perhaps just too foreign, for us to consider and thus cannot yield any real insight into what we think of as happiness. But this thought experiment is not as far from reality as we think. Consider alcohol or recreational drugs. People consume these substances in order to make themselves feel a certain way. But because of the damaging side effects, many people do not think the experience worth it. Is it so hard to imagine a type of drug that exaggerates the effects of, for example, heroin, and does not have any negative side effects? If not, then it seems that at least a crude version of the experience machine is not so far from our reality, after all.</p>

<p>If this answer still isn’t satisfactory, consider the following alternative scenario, which is not only possible, but happens in some form or another quite regularly: Imagine someone who is happily married to a wife whom he loves more than anything. He genuinely believes that his wife loves him in the same way, but in reality, she doesn’t love him at all. In reality, she is cheating on him and can put on a perfect act to make her husband believe the contrary. Should we say that the husband is truly happy, in the sense of <em>flourishing</em>? Is that the kind of “happiness” you would want for yourself? Put another way, if we compare two men, both of whom believe that they are loved by their wives, but only one of who actually is, would we say that they are equally well off? Or does the one with a truly loving wife have greater claim to being <em>truly</em> “happy”?</p>

<p>Having established that the Experience Machine (or the alternative experiment) is valuable to use as a thought experiment, I return to the question of why our intuition tells us to reject the offer to plug in to the machine. The answer is simple: we believe that happiness is more than just a psychological state. We value something else beyond simply experiencing certain emotions and believing certain things — we value <em>actually accomplishing</em> the things we think we are accomplishing and <em>actually being</em> the person we think we are. Striving to do things and to become a certain person seems completely meaningless if it all takes place in our heads. We pity the beguiled husband even though he believes that he is in a perfect marriage, because in reality, the marriage is broken. However, this position does not commit us to saying that mental states play <em>no</em> role in happiness. Rather, the claim I wish to advance is that mental states do not play the <em>only</em> role in happiness.</p>

<p>The question remains: What else do we value in our happiness? What else <em>should</em> we value in happiness? The question seem closely connected to what we <em>value </em> in that, what we value gives us a framework for evaluating whether or not any given individual is truly happy, and further, for determining how to live our lives in pursuit of happiness. For instance, someone who values that his life be grounded in reality and not some imaginary virtual machine will not think consider life in the Experience Machine to be one of genuine happiness.</p>

<p>After hearing these arguments, some may still want to plug in. If I asked these individuals to compare the <em>same</em> life in the experience machine, and the same life outside of the experience machine, however, I suspect most of them would regard the life outside the machine as “better” in some way. In this paper I have not argued <em>why</em> life outside the experience machine is the better alternative, or, more generally, why happiness <em>should</em> <em>not</em> consist only of mental states. This would involve a discussion of what we value and find meaningful. In this article, I hope to have at least shown that for most of us, who <em>do</em> have the intuition to refuse the experience machine, mental states are clearly not enough. Perhaps actual success or the actual possession of goods like truth, love, beauty, dignity, and freedom are intrinsically valuable and thus play a role in happiness.</p>

<p><em>Originally published in Flourish, Yale’s Undergraduate Journal for the Interdisciplinary Study of Human Flourishing</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on Metaphilosophy: The Role of Philosophy in My Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//reflections-on-metaphilosophy-the-role-of-philosophy-in-my-life"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//reflections-on-metaphilosophy-the-role-of-philosophy-in-my-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I wish I could say that I had a sudden realization, some profound epiphany concerning the human condition. It would be more thrilling for the reader. Unfortunately, the insights that I have reached through philosophy usually come about through a much more gradual, much less dramatic process. In compelling me to alter my understanding and interpretation of the world, the process can be dauntingly uncertain and even painful. I consider this very process of critical thought “philosophy.” But before I continue, I must clarify the meaning of this word. By philosophy, I mean the process of thinking, perceiving, and judging oneself and the world rationally in accordance with empirical knowledge. Philosophy also refers to the study of general and fundamental problems concerning truth, ethics, and human existence. I will address both in this essay. Nowadays people tend to have a negative conception of philosophy. The word invokes images of grand ivory towers situated behind ivy walls. Inside the towers in an oak-paneled room a pretentious old man sits on a gilded armchair, living in luxurious decadence. Out of touch with real world issues and having never encountered adversity, he spends his time contemplating ideas to amuse his intellect. This is not philosophy. In my experience, even educated people frequently misconceive of philosophy as an esoterically useless discipline meant only for an intelligentsia out of touch with the world. Among university students for instance, philosophy is one of the most ridiculed majors, right next to art history and English literature. This attitude towards philosophy has always infuriated me, not only because it shows the underlying ignorance of the believer, but also because of its glaring irony. The course of my life thus far has led me to firmly believe that philosophy is the most practical and necessary of all human disciplines.</p>

<p>I did not always believe in philosophy. In fact, I did not even know what philosophy was until sometime during my sophomore year of high school. Rather than being introduced to it or stumbling upon it by chance, I was eventually led to philosophy by my intellectual curiosity. In every class, as soon as I questioned the material on a deep enough level, the same type of apparently unanswerable questions would keep recurring. Biology class defined life as a series of ongoing chemical reactions and suggested that consciousness is the mere exchange of sodium and potassium ions across gated protein channels in the brain. In questioning these definitions, I hit upon philosophical discussions of defining human life, the existence the Platonic soul, and the existence of free will. In English class, reading Hamlet compelled me to consider the ethics of suicide and the possibility of living a meaningful existence despite life’s inevitable tragedies. Even math class, during our study of the summation of infinite series, caused me to contemplate the idea of infinity and the limits of the human mind in conceptualizing the infinite. These are but a few examples in the myriad questions I struggled with during high school.</p>

<p>As I began to systematically contemplate each of these questions, I noticed how they converged and oftentimes complemented one another. The debate about the existence of a soul coincides directly with the god debate. The discussion about free will relates to the ethics of suicide. Thus, not only does philosophy underlie the various academic subjects, but it ties everything together. It acts as a sort of interdisciplinary network, allowing me to synthesize information from one area with that of another. This synthesis allows me to produce conclusions, useful facts which I use to make decisions. In real life, decisions rarely require only a single area of knowledge. All human decisions necessitate thinking about various issues that branch into science, humanities, and other areas of thought. So in a sense, philosophy better prepares me to make real life decisions by making sense of knowledge in the context of all other types of knowledge. It is self-evident that no knowledge has any useful application unless it is contextualized with knowledge from other areas.</p>

<p>I have just discussed the importance of philosophy in the academic realm, but philosophy also exists as a powerful way of thinking. The German philosopher Nietzsche states, “There are no facts, only interpretations.” Apart from the debate of the possibility of absolute truth, there exists the simple fact that interpretation is a necessary and integral part of human perception. One might ask, “What about the objective truths derived from math and science?” I am referring to perception with the intent of applying the information. Of course the fact “one plus one equals two” leaves no room for interpretation. But to make use of it one must interpret this fact in the context of a real life situation. For instance, does falling in love and marrying somebody mean that the two of you exist as a single entity? Or do you both exist separately? What degree of agency should each retain in such a relationship? These questions depend on the understanding that quantities change when combined, but the meaning of such a fact must still be interpreted. In other words, although there are definite facts about the physical nature of the world, these are not truths in the strictly human sense. Knowing one plus one equals two does not inform us on how we should think about ourselves and the world. Hard facts must be interpreted, or humanized, in such a way that allows them to be applied to our lives. It is through this very process of human interpretation that we construct our reality. Philosophy refines the way one interprets the information he receives. The philosophical approach to interpretation entails constantly thinking about external information and cross-referencing it with other facts, with the ultimate goal of reaching a useful and informed conclusion. By approaching the world with a severely critical eye that questions every iota of information it receives, one can reach the most objective conception of the given situation. This involves understanding the various internal biases of both the information giver and receiver. As discussed above, humans operate based on interpretation, not hard fact. No matter how hard they try to give an objective account, it is necessarily influenced by subjective interpretation. Furthermore, one’s own reception of information is unavoidably skewed by internal biases. People often bend things to hear what they want. Philosophy works to counter this two sided subjectivity, allowing one to reach the most objective reality. I had to steel myself with this mentality during the college search process.</p>

<p>Every year during the summer and fall, colleges unleash impressively aggravating advertising campaigns involving tons of paper, emails, and phone calls. In its wake lie acres of deforestation, overflowing spam folders, and millions of poor misled students. Colleges like to personally address the letters to students by first name, writing in a friendly tone hoping to draw them in. They use numbers to boast about the number of Nobel prizes their faculty have received, their annual endowment, and the racial diversity of the student body. They present their institution as alone possessing these characteristics, existing as the most perfect place in the world for you to spend the next four years. I can imagine how the unsuspecting high school junior can easily get lassoed by this type of advertising. In order to find a truly well-fitting college, I approached the process fully aware of the marketing strategies these institutions employed. Furthermore, I understood that the colleges I was applying to are essentially similar with regards to academic quality, diversity of student body, and social atmosphere, differing only in location and other minor characteristics. This approach, I would imagine, spared me the stress of desperately wanting to be accepted to the only college I thought would suit me. I realized that I was applying to a number of colleges I would be very happy at, and that in the end, the experience will depend more on how I use the institution’s resources rather than what resources it provided me. By attaining the most objective reality of the situation, I was able to create the most beneficial interpretation.</p>

<p>Part of interpreting a fact includes determining how valuable that fact is. As humans, we live our lives doing, or with the hope of doing, what we want. We only want what matters to us, what is meaningful and what is valuable. Philosophy aids me on this quest for existential meaning because what I care about is often not easily apparent. It requires a combination of life experiences and deep contemplation to realize what I truly care about. I’m not talking about simple pleasures which can be discovered through reflexive emotional responses. Watching an entertaining movie makes me happy, but the happiness is also shallow and temporary. Simple thrills do not motivate me in the long run. What makes life worth living is the promise of experiencing true, lasting meaning. For instance, it took me many years to fully appreciate my musical education. I always hated practicing and listening to jazz and classical music when I was younger. Now, listening and playing such music gives me a feeling of satisfaction that I don’t get from anything else. Although this may have been a result of my acclimation to music after studying it for so many years, I think the full explanation must acknowledge the fact that I tried to understand and relate to the meaning behind the music. After eight years of study, I know with certainty that I value jazz and classical music on the deepest level.</p>

<p>Having a philosophical state of mind means constantly questioning not only the accuracy of one’s perceptions but also the quality of one’s valuations. It is easy to convince yourself that you enjoy something you actually don’t. Although I have no experience with this, my older brother David shared his experience in the job market and the realizations he’s come to. He told me about how fresh college graduates are frequently misled by jobs with high salaries, not considering the value of the work itself. After graduating, my brother was offered jobs by banks and consulting firms with impressive salaries, but these were jobs that didn’t interest him. Instead he chose to explore the tech-startup industry, working for smaller groups with more modest salaries and lacking the financial benefits of large corporations. Because of this, he’s discovered a passion for computer programming and web development, something he never would’ve been exposed to had he decided to work for a bank. I’m sure that many adults find themselves in the doldrums of a job they hate, realizing after many miserable years that the salary does not outweigh the negatives of the work itself. This can be avoided if one always knows and prioritizes what he deeply values. Through this rationalization, one can easily conclude that money should be treated as a means, not as an end. Philosophy can help one realize that it is not money that is valuable, but rather the possibilities that money provides. By constantly reevaluating my values, I emerge with a more absolute and profound awareness of what is meaningful to me. Philosophy acts as an intellectual sieve, filtering out the refuse and ensuring that what remains is truly valuable to oneself.</p>

<p>I’ve offered my thoughts on the academic importance of philosophy as well as its personal importance in attaining the most objective conception of the world and in striving for true meaning. But the question still remains, what is philosophy? Defining it is difficult because it exists in so many different forms and contexts. In the broadest sense, I consider philosophy an intellectual process which uses reason to investigate and interpret the nature of oneself, one’s environment, and the relationship of the two. Furthermore, philosophy is an internal mode of thinking that is reliable under all external circumstances. In its most ideal form, philosophy should exist as a universal approach to human problems, from the mundane to the profound. Emphasis is placed on reason because only through systematic logic one can effectively determine consistency and inconsistency, and consequentially, right versus wrong and value versus lack of value. All of this philosophical thinking leads to the ultimate purpose of deciding how to live one’s life.</p>

<p>Only by first evaluating the world and oneself objectively can one then decide how to act, acting being the interface between the self and the environment. Only by first answering the question “What is?” can one answer “What should be?” Everyday life demands decisions from us of varying degrees, compelling us to ask ourselves what is moral and immoral. This dilemma presents itself to me every time I choose to illegally pirate music. On one hand, it’s against the law and could have very serious legal ramifications if caught. On the other hand, the artists of the music I pirate already passed away. Their estates would receive all of the commissions from purchases. Knowing them to be artists in the purest sense, I can comfortably conclude that they would rather want people to be exposed to their musical artistry and genius than for their estates to earn money. This is an example of how philosophy remains essential dealing with the question of “How should I act?” Philosophy rationally organizes one’s knowledge and principles to allow this question to be adequately addressed. Because I am constantly exposed to new situations and gaining new knowledge, my answers to this question constantly fluctuates. It is easy to stop considering new information, unintentionally reverting to an outdated ethical mode. As shown by history, the individual’s failure to update their opinions with new facts can lead to disastrous injustices. I remember feeling deeply disturbed when studying about events like the Holocaust, the Rape of Nanjing, and the My Lai Massacre. How could these things happen? How could human beings commit such terrible atrocities to one another, not only murdering and raping but also torturing and mutilating. What happened to the common sense and rational instinct that should have been screaming for an end? These are unanswered questions which will continue to haunt me. But part of the answer, I think, is the fact that the individuals relinquished their ability to independently reason and valuate. Hannah Arendt says, “The sad truth is that most evil is done by people who never make up their minds to be good or evil.” I agree with her idea of the “banality of evil,” that more often than not, human injustice is a result of a lack of thinking, and consequentially the lack of exercising good will. Evil does not arise from actively sinful perpetrators but rather from passively unthinking and prejudiced bystanders. The philosophical mindset both prevents the individual from succumbing to the prejudices of his own complacent intellect and that of others. The philosopher exists as an active agent promoting active thought and thus spreading active morality.</p>

<p>My life has led me to philosophy not out of choice, but out of necessity. My education and personal experiences demand that I answer questions which require a rigorous type of thinking satisfied only by philosophy. For me, the question that will always remain at the core of my life is “What makes life worth living?” More specifically, what makes my life worth living? All other philosophical questions lead to this one. Inquiries into the nature of the universe, one’s identity, and the proper ethics both depend on and help answer this singular question. It is one which is expressed in the art and literature of every era from every region of the world. Contemplation of this question remains at the core of the fundamental human experience. In this sense, there is a touching element of human tragedy to philosophy, that it paradoxically strives to answer a question that has no objectively definitive answer. There is something inexplicably beautiful and deeply inspiring about this Sisyphean struggle. As a philosopher, I’ve come to realize that one does not attain meaning by simply answering the question conclusively and putting the matter to rest. Rather, meaning is found in the very process of attempting to find an answer. What has made my life worth living are all of the things I’ve experienced during my philosophical quest, from the inspiring to the tragic, from the profound to the mundane, from the beautiful to the grotesque. What makes life worth living is the chance to be a philosopher – the opportunity to engage in this existential dialectic, to experience what it means to be human and to know what it means to be me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
