<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title><![CDATA[Harvey Xia]]></title>
	<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//"/>
	<updated>2015-07-27T19:24:32-04:00</updated>
	<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Harvey Xia]]></name>
		<email><![CDATA[harvey@harveyxia.com]]></email>
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Flood Channels]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-flood-channels"/>
		<updated>2014-05-02T22:09:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-flood-channels</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Beneath Las Vegas are miles of underground tunnels leading out of the city in all directions. “Underground tunnels” probably evokes images of hazardous, claustrophobic places, full of rusting pipes, electrical wires, and steam valves. But these tunnels are not part of the sewage or electrical system. They were meant solely to control floods. In the unlikely event of heavy rain, the city, being situated in a valley, would be flooded if not for these channels directing water away from the city into vast desert basins.</p>

<p>A few years ago Jason discovered an entrance to the channels by the desert next to his house. From a distance, it looked insignificant—cement walls topped by wire fences, like just another municipal structure. Walking up to it, I saw that the walls maintained a section dug out of the hill. On the wall facing into the center of Vegas was a square tunnel, as wide and tall as a single lane road. Jason handed me a flashlight and we headed in.</p>

<p>Except for the occasional manhole cover that led into the tunnels, they were bare of any structural features. These tunnels were simply long chambers of grey concrete. Occasional painted numbers, six digits long, marked the distance.</p>

<p>After a few minutes of walking, I glanced over my shoulder. A wall of pitch black met my eyes. Switching off the flashlight left us in total darkness. We were somewhere in the middle of this mile long tunnel.</p>

<p>The air was dry and cool. A slight draft constantly swept through. Combined with the utter darkness, the lack of sound became equally unsettling. Unused to total silence, my ears became jittery, expecting to hear something at each successive moment, but hearing nothing, like that feeling of unbearable suspense one gets immersed a well-crafted horror film. This hyper-expectant state made me hyper-sensitive. Occasionally, a car would run over a manhole cover, causing a sudden, jarring clunk to echo through the tunnel. My body jolted at each random sonic impulse of iron against iron, sustained and amplified down the concrete chamber.</p>

<p>After what felt like an hour of walking, we emerged from the other side into the sunlight. A wave of relieving sensory phenomena washed in. My eyes and ears once again bathed in the sights and sounds of the world. This section of the channel was exposed to the sky—clouds passed slowly overhead, airplanes droned, the highway roared softly in the distance. Caught in the wind, plastic bags whirled about with choreographic elegance. Empty, half crushed beer cans clanked along.</p>

<p>The floor was littered with trash: bottles, newspapers, plastic bags, ragged clothing, anything that the previous rain had carried with it. More and more frequently we saw signs of previous inhabitants. Dark smoke stains rising on the walls. Dirty mattresses. Bicycles hung up to avoid being washed away. I wondered if anyone lived in such an isolated place, and if we would encounter them. Probably not, I thought. This place felt like a ghost town.</p>

<p>The channel widened. The walls rose higher. I saw graffiti, most of it just a mess of neon lines layered on top each other. “HOLE” in large, ugly block letters, an arrow beside it pointing to a hole in the wall. Numerous hastily drawn penises drawn in two circles and a stretched out “U”. Beneath a red scrawl lay the image of a face painted in purple. Angular lines outlined its eyes, eyebrows, nose, and mouth in a way that implied the rest. The resulting gaze was so striking that we stopped to stare back it.</p>

<p>More and more frequently lateral tunnel openings appeared on either side. Other channels converged upon this one, Jason said. We were walking along one of the main channels that led to a wash. I looked down one these side tunnels, only ten feet wide and a few feet tall. Deep inside the tunnel obscured in the dark was a mattress, pots, a blue tarp, plastic water bottles, and other things I couldn’t identify. Part of me wondered if that lump on the mattress was a person.</p>

<p>Sometime later we encountered a man camped out in the channels. Hidden in the darkness, he spotted us first and whistled to get our attention. Instinctively I turned off the flashlight and stopped, my heart pounding, legs tensed up and ready to sprint back. Jason, a seasoned channel explorer, called out to the man, asking permission to pass. “Sure, go ahead,” the man said. I cautiously follow Jason forward as he approached him. Jason offered him food and water, but he declined. Besides being unshaven the middle aged man appeared in good condition. His clothes weren’t ragged. He had a mattress, pillow, and a cart full of food and water. I spotted a large knife lying on his bed within arms reach. Later, Jason explained that people down here need a way to defend themselves: “Being alone in this kind of place, you need to be prepared for anything.”</p>

<p>“We’re just passing through, I’m showing my friend around.”</p>

<p>The man nodded his head. “Keep reading the bible. The Revelation is coming.”</p>

<p>He went on to warn us about the apocalyptic dangers ahead. Instead of preaching to us the typical fire-and-brimstone voice of urgency, he spoke to us casually, nodding his head for emphasis. We asked him once again if he wanted food or water. He shook his head, insisting he was fine. As we walked on, I wondered if he really was fine. I wondered if he denied our help out of dignity, under some illusion that he was okay. I resisted the urge to glance back. Planes droned and the highway hummed in the background. All of it seemed far away in the distance.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/floodchannels.jpg" class="fancybox" title=""><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/floodchannels.jpg"  alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Photo by Jason Kim.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[An Aging Memory]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//an-aging-memory"/>
		<updated>2014-03-25T13:46:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//an-aging-memory</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>My earliest memory is a series of discrete images. A slideshow rather than a scene. The gaps in the pictures obscure what was happening in the memory, leaving me with a collection of words devoid of verbs. There are, however, plenty of nouns and adjectives.</p>

<p>The memory begins with a small, aluminum, semispherical bowl. It was the bowl my grandmother used to feed me with, though if I were being good she would let me attempt it myself — a chopstick in each hand, determined to manipulate the food into my mouth but usually failing. There was something green in the bowl, probably some sort of Chinese vegetable given how much I love vegetables now.</p>

<p>I was in the cramped dining room of my grandparents’ old apartment in Sanming, a dusty industrial place. The bottom of the walls were painted an ugly shade of turquoise, the top half a discolored white. Across one side of the room were big windows that faced the apartment complex’s courtyard. Small potted plants sat on the windowsill. I forget what they looked like.</p>

<p>A soft, yellow light diffused about the room, softening edges and blurring lines, as if turning down the sharpness on a TV. I can’t be sure whether this was how it actually looked, or if my memory has literally faded over time like an old photograph. As I envision the room now, it seems more and more to resemble a sepia print. The memory, the mental image, seems to age as I invoke it. Or perhaps the memory grows clearer, revealing the agedness of the room itself.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[On Journaling and Recordkeeping]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//on-journaling-and-recordkeeping"/>
		<updated>2014-03-24T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//on-journaling-and-recordkeeping</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>I used to write in my journal all the time in high school, especially between when school ended and when my parents came home. The quietness and boredom of the house brought my inner thoughts into focus. Journaling, then, was my way of managing these thoughts, a way to force the mental torrent into a stream of discrete and lucid ideas.</p>

<p>To maintain a habit of journaling, it seems necessary to have a river of thoughts compelling one to pick up the pen. But the roaring torrent diminishes to a stream when the days get busier. The mind has other tasks to focus on. Responsibilities take precedence over introspection.</p>

<p>As I explored the mountains, valleys, and canyons of Zion, I felt a different tension keeping me from journaling: the desire for a pure and undistracted experience. Journaling, photography, and any other kind of personal recordkeeping place me in the reflective mode. Recordkeeping involves picking and choosing what to jot down, what to take a picture of, requiring that I sift through my immediate memories for the significant ones.</p>

<p>To reflect in this way is to view the present from an elevated perspective, which not only brings me out of the moment’s immediacy, but also transposes my attention from the external world to the internal mind. It seems a shame to dilute the raw and sensory impressions by notebook or camera. There will be time for that later when the day is done.</p>

<p>But at the same time, I want to capture the very experience I’m afraid of diluting, so that I can remember or perhaps even relive it. This internal conflict afflicts writers and those with literary or artistic sensibilities. Does an ideal balance exist between experience and reflection, between the possibilities of living in the moment and reliving the past?</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Flood Channels]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-flood-channels"/>
		<updated>2014-03-23T21:35:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-flood-channels</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Beneath Las Vegas are miles of tunnels leading out of the city in all directions. Made of cement and wide enough for cars, they are known as the <em>flood channels</em>. In the unlikely event of heavy rain, the city, being in a valley, would be flooded. The flood channels do exactly what their name suggests: they channel water from the city to the surrounding desert.</p>

<p>A few years ago Jason discovered an entrance to the channels by the desert next to his house. From a distance, it looked insignificant—cement walls surrounded by wire fences. It looked like just another municipal structure, for the sewage system maybe. Walking up to it, I saw that the walls outlined a section dug out of the hill. On the wall facing into the hill (and into Vegas proper) was a square tunnel, as wide and tall as a single lane road. Jason handed me a flashlight and we headed in.</p>

<p>After a few minutes of walking, I glanced over my shoulder. A wall of pitch blackness met my eyes. Switching off the flashlight left us in total darkness. We were somewhere near the middle of this mile long tunnel.</p>

<p>The floor was littered with trash: bottles, newspapers, plastic bags, ragged clothing, anything that the rain had carried with it. Occasionally we saw signs of previous inhabitants. Dark smoke stains rising to a point on the walls. Dirty mattresses. Bicycles hung up to avoid being washed away. Part of me wondered if that lump in the mattress was a person. I wondered if we would encounter anyone in such a dark and isolated place.</p>

<p>I could hear nothing but the sound of our own footsteps and breathing. Occasionally, a car would run over a manhole cover, causing a sudden, jarring clunk to echo throughout the tunnel. I quickened my pace, waiting to see the distant glint of the other end.</p>

<p><a href="https://scontent-b-iad.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-frc3/t1.0-9/544628_419618904719536_1920774910_n.jpg"><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/floodchannels.jpg" alt="Flood Channels" /></a></p>

<p>Photo by Jason Kim.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Meadows]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-meadows"/>
		<updated>2014-03-22T20:25:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-meadows</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Las Vegas is Spanish for “the meadows.” It used to be a green valley in the middle of endless desert. Now it has become what is considered the “Entertainment Capital of the World,” notorious as a bastion of hedonism, a place adults go to have shameless fun. When others hear that Jason and I are going to Vegas for spring break, they tell us we’ll have an awesome time, half smiling half smirking.</p>

<p>Jason lives in the Vegas suburbs. He wanted to show me the side of Vegas that wasn’t just blinding lights and glittering casinos and flashy dancers. He and his three siblings grew up with the desert hills in their backyard. When he was younger they would go to the desert to shoot airsoft guns. In high school, the desert gave him a quiet place to hike and be surrounded by nature.</p>

<p>He took me to the top of the “ridge,” a tall and steep hill that seemed to be crumbling away. Besides some small cacti, the landscape was comprised of nothing but sand and rock. It was windy. I could see for miles around me. In the distance, perhaps hundreds of miles away, were the shapes of mountains, more and more faded as they receded.</p>

<p>From here, the city looked like arrangement of tiny blocks of different heights. It was small compared to the vastness of the entire valley—the last thing someone would think standing on the strip. As the sun set, lights began turning on until the entire city became a sea of orange. Together, the lights appeared to shimmer. The sky was cloudless. A full moon lit our way down the hill and back to the road.</p>

<p><a href="https://scontent-a-lga.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-frc3/l/t31.0-8/1957647_828258610522228_247810185_o.jpg"><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/vegas.jpg" alt="Vegas" /></a></p>

<p>Photo by Jason Kim.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Faces of Zion]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//faces-of-zion"/>
		<updated>2014-03-20T14:26:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//faces-of-zion</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>The road took me around a bend and revealed a ring of mountains. They towered over me not from a distance, but as if I was at their very feet. Sandy with streaks of iron red, their bare, flat peaks blotted out much of the sky. As I drove deeper into Zion, the mountain seemed to converge on the valley—two walls of stone closing in on either side.</p>

<p>Being walled in is how I felt hiking the Narrows, Zion’s slot canyon carved out by the Virgin River. There’s a section if it called “Wall Street.” The park ranger said, “You’ll know it when you see it.” It being March, the water was still cold from snowmelt. Jason and I wrapped ourselves up in dry suits that made us look like Star Trekkers, and headed into the opening of the mountain wall from which a river flowed. What began as a leisurely walk through an inch deep stream soon turned into a battle against a forceful current, forcing us to wade through chest deep water. The underlying rocks were smooth and covered with algae, perfect for stealing your balance and letting the river sweep you off your feet.</p>

<p>Two miles and two hours later, we stopped for a short break. I hadn’t noticed until then that the river had narrowed down to only around 20 feet wide. 300 feet of sheer vertical rock left only a sliver of visible sky. Sunlight could not reach down here. Everything was lit by a dim grey light reflected off stony surfaces.</p>

<p>The deeper we hiked, the more I seemed to see faces in the walls. Its smooth contours occasionally being accented by hard edges bore a remarkable resemblance to the human face, like the Easter Island heads. These colossal heads only revealed themselves when viewed upstream, their indifferent eyes directed into the canyon path as if looking ahead. When I turned to look back the faces were nowhere to be seen, hidden in the canyon grooves.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/zionfaces.jpg" alt="Zion's Faces" /></p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Through the Desert]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//through-the-desert"/>
		<updated>2014-03-15T11:47:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//through-the-desert</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Only when I drove to Zion did I understand the extent of Vegas’ geographical isolation — it really is in the middle of nowhere. Towering over all 360 degrees of the horizon, mountains constantly impose their presence over the valley. At night by plane, Vegas appears as a sea of shimmering orange light in the otherwise black nothingness; an oasis of civilization.</p>

<p>My roommate Jason and I went north on US-93, a highway that began with four lanes of traffic. Later, immediately outside of Vegas, it dwindled to a single lane of mostly cargo trucks. Several miles outside of the city, we were fully immersed in the Nevadan desert. Below the horizon extended a plane of dusty yellow sand dotted with stunted, hardy-looking plants. At the horizon, jagged mountains pierced upwards, sometimes with snowcapped tips. A cloudless sky arched from their peaks over the ground. All of the landscape’s colors appeared washed out as if faded by sunlight.</p>

<p>As someone who had only ever seen the eastern Appalachian scenery of New England, what most struck me about the desert was its expansiveness, how the eye could see all the way into the disappearing horizon. I felt dwarfed by the vastness of the open sky, the open desert, and the encircling mountains. Nothing was hidden behind forests or skyscrapers. All was transparent.</p>

<p>Jason and I had long since stopped talking. As the sun descended behind craggy silhouettes, the desert took on a calm glow. Textures gave way to shapes and lines. Looking into the distance, I was under the illusion that we were motionless while desert slowly flowed past, suspended in its boundlessness.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/desert_road.jpg" alt="Desert Road" /></p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Hack Your Workflow]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//hack-your-workflow"/>
		<updated>2014-02-07T15:30:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//hack-your-workflow</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Since I started coding a year ago, I&#8217;ve learned many useful practices that have drastically increased my coding efficiency, both for CS psets and web/software development. This post is a catalog of best practices and hackerish tricks that I&#8217;ve picked up. It should be helpful especially to those who so far have only coded in an academic setting where none of this is discussed. These tools should help you spend less time fussing with your utilities, giving you more time to work on solving problems and building things.</p>

<p>(Note that this guide is primarily written for Mac users. I&#8217;m not sure if all apps/tools carry over to PC and Linux)</p>

<h2>Using the Terminal</h2>

<h3>Tip 1: <a href="http://www.iterm2.com/#/section/features/256_colors">Download iTerm2</a></h3>

<p>Don&#8217;t just use the built in Mac terminal. iTerms 2 a terminal emulator that has great features. For instance, it lets you open multiple tabs for multiple terminal sessions, and has 256 colors. Generally it looks and feels better than the default Mac terminal.</p>

<h3>Tip 2: Use zshell and personalize it</h3>

<p>I use zsh mainly for its powerful autocompletion. This helps with finding/selecting files and directories. Instead of just listing matched items like bash, Zsh allows you to tab through them and select the one you want, saving you a lot of typing. Zsh also expands the path for you if matches a single directory. Here I type <code>cd</code> and tab through:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com/images/zsh_autocomplete.gif" alt="Zsh autocomplete" /></p>

<p>Another reason to use zsh is that you can customize its appearance. Here is my terminal:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com/images/my_terminal.png" alt="My Terminal" /></p>

<p>You can change your prompt to include info like your working directory, the date, system diagnostics (CPU and RAM usage, etc), even the weather. People typically use <a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">oh-my-zsh</a> to manage and install zsh packages. As for my zsh theme, I took it from my brother David. It&#8217;s included in his workflow <a href="https://github.com/davidxia/bootstrap_dotfiles">configuration script</a>.</p>

<h3>Tip 3: Get Good With Linux Commands.</h3>

<p>Here are the two resources I used to learn the basic commands, as well as how the system directory works: <a href="http://www.funtoo.org/Linux_Fundamentals,_Part_1">Linux Fundamentals</a>, <a href="http://www.linfo.org/index.html">Linux Information Project</a>. Having to look up commands such as <em>cd, ls, touch</em>, etc. can really slow you down. Once you memorize them, navigating folders with commands is as fast, if not faster, than doing through an operating system&#8217;s GUI.</p>

<p>Here are some useful unix commands:</p>

<p><code>cat</code>, <code>head</code>, and <code>tail</code> — displays the entire, beginning, or end of file. Use flag <code>-n x</code> to display first or last x lines</p>

<p><code>ls</code> — list files in current directory. <code>-l</code> gives additional information and <code>-a</code> shows hidden files denoted by period.</p>

<p><code>mv</code> — moves files, renames files or folders</p>

<p><code>mkdir</code> — create folder</p>

<p><code>rm</code> — deletes file</p>

<p><code>touch</code> — creates file</p>

<h3>Tip 4: Use tab completion.</h3>

<p>This one can really save you time. There&#8217;s no need to type out a long file or folder name if you can just do it in one keystroke. Furthermore, tab completion will pattern match and list all the items that start with the characters you&#8217;ve entered. This is an easy way to examine folder contents without an explicit <code>ls</code>.</p>

<h3>Tip 5: Use the up and down arrows.</h3>

<p>It pains me to see coders not use this. Scroll through your most recent commands using the up and down arrows.</p>

<h3>Tip 6: Use reverse search.</h3>

<p>Ctrl-R opens a program that, given a keyword, searches your command history for previous commands that contain that keyword. Repeatedly pressing Ctrl-R will cycle through them. This eliminates the need to retype or paste a long command that you can&#8217;t remember.</p>

<p>Also, the <code>history</code> command will list previously typed commands.</p>

<h3>Tip 7: Get Autojump</h3>

<p>This program, <a href="https://github.com/joelthelion/autojump">available here</a>, makes it incredibly easy to get around to the folders you need to. Autojump remembers folders you&#8217;ve CD&#8217;ed to, and ranks them based on frequency of use. When entering a keyword, it will match against that list and return the most frequently used folder. So, instead of typing <code>~/harvey/Desktop/School/.../CS223</code>, I can simply type <code>j 223</code>.</p>

<h2>Working Remotely</h2>

<p>Oftentimes we need to work using a remote server. This section should be especially helpful for Yale CS students accessing the Zoo. Instead of using fastX or other annoying file transfer programs you can access the Zoo server directly through your terminal.</p>

<h3>Tip 1: SSH</h3>

<p>The <code>ssh</code> command allows you to connect to a server. To connect to the zoo, you would type:</p>

<pre><code>ssh netID@node.zoo.cs.yale.edu
</code></pre>

<p>To save time, I recommend setting up an ssh config file located at <code>~/.ssh/config</code> and creating a shortcut name that automatically enters the correct user and address.</p>

<ol>
<li>cd to your <code>~/</code> directory and check if you have a .ssh folder (use <code>ls -a</code>)</li>
<li>If you don&#8217;t, simply create one using <code>mkdir .ssh</code></li>
<li>Enter the folder and create or edit a &#8220;config&#8221; file.</li>
<li><p>Enter the following:</p>

<pre><code> Host zoo
 HostName lion.zoo.cs.yale.edu
 User (your netID)
</code></pre></li>
</ol>


<p>To avoid having to enter a password, you can add your RSA public key to the authorized_keys folder of the zoo. All of that (including how to create a public/private RSA keypair) is <a href="http://www.linuxproblem.org/art_9.html">detailed here</a>.</p>

<h3>Tip 2: SCP</h3>

<p>Say you&#8217;ve been working locally and you&#8217;re ready to test your script against Stan&#8217;s public test cases. You can transfer file(s) to and from the server using the <code>scp</code> command. Here is an example:</p>

<p><code>scp Binpack.c log.c makefile zoo:cs223/PSET2/</code></p>

<p>This command means, transfer the following files: Binpack.C, log.c, and makefile to the zoo server, specifically in the folder cs223/PSET2/.</p>

<p>To scp something from the server, simply place the remote file first, and the local directory second.</p>

<p><code>scp zoo:cs223/PSET2/Binpack.c .</code></p>

<h2>Use <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/3">Sublime Text</a> for coding</h2>

<p>Programmers all have different preferences for how they write code. Some like to use IDE&#8217;s, others like using text editors.</p>

<p>If you are using a text editor, don&#8217;t use emacs or notepad. You should be using an editor that at least has syntax-highlighting. This makes writing, reading, and debugging code much easier by outlining syntactic information visually.</p>

<p>Among text editors, the two most popular are Vim and Sublime Text. Vim is a command line program that relies on keystrokes to do things. It&#8217;s hard to get used to, but experience Vim users can edit text quickly, using a few number of keystrokes. There&#8217;s even a site called <a href="http://vimgolf.com/">Vimgolf</a>, where players are challenged to do things in the fewest keystrokes possible.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s a big debate on whether to use Vim or Sublime Text. I think both are great and the right choice depends on the coder. Personally, I use Sublime Text because I&#8217;m more used to GUI style typing. I like being able to click somewhere to place my cursor, and not having to worry about switching being typing mode and command mode. Originally I was going to learn Vim, but I decided it wasn&#8217;t worth the first few weeks or months of slower coding.</p>

<p>There are so many awesome features built in to Sublime as well as in add-on packages. The following are the main settings and packages I use:</p>

<ol>
<li>line ruler at the 80 character mark</li>
<li>use 4 spaces for tabs (never use tabs for indents, they can sometimes cause compile errors)</li>
<li>highlight current line</li>
<li>Sublime Linter (lints my code for trivial syntactic errors)</li>
<li>Valign (lines up surrounding vertically based on syntax)</li>
</ol>


<p>Here are my user settings:</p>

<pre><code>{
"auto_complete_commit_on_tab": true,
"bold_folder_labels": true,
"caret_style": "phase",
"color_scheme": "Packages/User/Solarized (Dark) (SL).tmTheme",
"font_size": 13.0,
"highlight_line": true,
"highlight_modified_tabs": true,
"ignored_packages":
[
    "Vintage"
],
"line_padding_bottom": 1,
"line_padding_top": 1,
"rulers":
[
    80
],
"translate_tabs_to_spaces": true,
"word_wrap": true,
"wrap_width": 100
}
</code></pre>

<h2><a href="http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized">Solarized Colors</a></h2>

<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/solarized.png" alt="Solarized" /></p>

<p>At first I didn&#8217;t understand why it seemed like all the hackers I saw used this dark bluish color scheme. But then I tried it out. Something about the combination of colors make this color scheme incredibly pleasing to the eye. I&#8217;ve tried other color schemes to keep things interesting, but I always revert back to solarized. What&#8217;s nice is that since it&#8217;s so popular, there&#8217;s a solarized theme for almost everything out there.</p>

<p>Try it out, I bet you&#8217;ll like it.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Distractions of College]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-distractions-of-college"/>
		<updated>2013-11-26T15:56:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-distractions-of-college</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been trying to write a blog post for a few weeks now, but I couldn&#8217;t seem to follow through with it, for reasons that I&#8217;ll try my best to articulate. My hope is that trying to put these nebulous feelings into words will help me figure out just what it is that I&#8217;ve been feeling, it seems, more and more intensely since the beginning of college — this unsettling feeling that I&#8217;m losing some nameless quality of myself, the value of which I can intuitively sense but can&#8217;t articulate; an unsettling feeling that colors all of my experiences with the question <em>Does this matter?</em>, and an urgency to do and experience things that, beyond a doubt, have meaning. I realize that all of this sounds very existential. I would agree. But what I&#8217;m experiencing can&#8217;t simply be pigeonholed into the stereotypical &#8220;existential crisis.&#8221; From talking with friends and reading various essays, <sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup> it seems that I&#8217;m not the only one struggling with the questions I&#8217;m about to raise. (In fact, what inspired me to write this in the first place was an anonymous email that a Yale student sent out commenting on Yale&#8217;s culture).</p>

<p>Late on a Friday night after an exhausting week, I was determined to write a blog post much like the one I&#8217;m attempting now. I wrote the following:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/calvinandhobbes_summer.gif"></p>

<blockquote><blockquote><p>I love this sentiment in <em>Calvin and Hobbes</em>, the idea that in certain moments, the best thing to do is to do nothing at all. Of course, here Calvin and Hobbes aren&#8217;t literally doing nothing at all; they&#8217;re sitting back and taking in the beautiful summer day. It makes me think of those perfect summer days where the tree you are sitting under casts a generous shade while the sun above sets the surrounding scenary in the most flattering light. Cool grass between your fingers and toes, gentle winds rustling the leaves. Everything feels, sounds, and looks perfect, invoking a feeling of complete carefree laziness. At its very best, it feels as if you&#8217;ve been transported to a place where your day-to-day worries are so distant that they cease to exist, where being lazy is the virtue.</p>

<p>In the quieter, less hectic moments of my college life, I find myself missing that feeling more and more. At college, my attention is constantly drawn outwards towards classes, activities, internships, and all of that other stuff that American college students are expected to be doing. In high school I suffered through the college application process with the hope that once I got to college, I could focus on learning and making friends and growing. But it doesn&#8217;t end. I guess this could be the beginning of what they call the &#8220;rat race.&#8221; There&#8217;s no more time to just be, in the most primitive sense of the word. There&#8217;s no time to sit in bed and read, to listen to music, or to go for a walk on a nice autumn day. Rather, there is time, but that free time is treated as a luxury too valuable for wasting on &#8220;doing nothing.&#8221;
For the college student, even his leisure time is&#8230;</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>I stopped midsentence, choosing instead to numb my mind by browsing Reddit and playing Dota. It wasn&#8217;t that I didn&#8217;t want to keep writing, but that it was a Friday night — one of the few times during the week that I get to kickback and give my brain a desperately needed rest after a long week of overclocking it on psets and readings. Leisure writing is, of course, a kind of break from the monotony of school and homework. It&#8217;s an escape from the restricted, logical, and analytical thinking that my classes require. It&#8217;s a way to step back from it all — to enter a quiet, isolated, and introspective mode. Writing takes me out of the groundlevel perspective of everyday life to an elevated viewpoint, one that is one step removed from it all, allowing me to think about myself and my life more honestly and deliberately.</p>

<p>Why couldn&#8217;t I get myself to write more than two paragraphs? Because reflective first-person writing is taxing on the mind in the same way that my classes are. While the reflective me was desperate to have itself heard, the rest of me was simply too tired, not willing to expend effort on anything. I could instead browse reddit while my mind slept. <em>After all,</em> the practical me thought, <em>it&#8217;s not like I would get any real reward from writing something just for the sake of writing it. Why expend effort on anything that has no return value?</em> But this is just the harmful sort of belief that I&#8217;ve let myself gradually and unconsciously adopt since I&#8217;ve come to Yale. The truth is, reflective self-expression takes an enormous amount of deliberate effort, and moreso, the capacity for insightful thinking diminishes with lack of use. Being constantly preoccupied with classes and extracurriculars and events, I gradually stopped journaling and writing and enjoying  lazy Sunday afternoons. There was always something &#8220;more productive&#8221; to do.</p>

<p>This is what I&#8217;ve slowly been realizing since college started, that Yale&#8217;s academic and social culture and my own lack of effort can turn me away from the creative, self-reflective aspect of me. The aspect I think of when I&#8217;m asked to describe myself. The part of me I consider as the source of who I am, as my persistent anchor of identity. But &#8220;lack of effort&#8221; doesn&#8217;t quite characterize it properly; it&#8217;s more like my lack of consciously being aware of these external distractions and giving myself more time to reflect. I think this is the root of that unsettling feeling that I&#8217;m losing something important of myself; my day to day college life leaves me so tired that I make excuses when I do have time to do some hard thinking by myself.</p>

<p>At college, it seems, everyone&#8217;s attention is drawn outward and away from themselves, and the culture glorifies this. You&#8217;re a rockstar if your calendar is filled to the brim with overlapping commitments, your extracurricular activites outnumber your classes, you&#8217;ve secured a prestigious  internship. And the ideal social life is very much analogous to this: you&#8217;re doing it right if your social nights consist of hopping from one party to the next and on to Toad&#8217;s, your romantic life (or, sex life, rather) consists of hooking up with various people, especially if others consider them desirable, and then waking up the next morning retelling the events of last night at brunch in the same humorously self-deprecating way that is really just a veil for your own pride that you are, in fact, living up the college life.</p>

<p>And that&#8217;s that, without a second thought. Brunch ends and you automatically move on to the next set of tasks: completing those homework assignments. And the weeks repeat like this over and over. There&#8217;s not a moment to spare in between, no time to take a breath and step back from it all. Life is lived passively, reflexively, and robotically from one moment to the next. The mind loses itself in things that seem important but upon examination are really just inflated trivialities. And the effect of college, it seems, is to perpetuate this type of thinking in us, the type that distracts us from considering and pursuing what really matters.</p>

<p>Now, what really matters is of course different for all of us, but I do think that for everyone, what matters comes into focus only through hard and honest thought — thinking in the normative mode, looking for an answer in a domain where it isn&#8217;t clear whether an answer even exists, let alone what that answer is. It demands the courage to revolt against the values that are given to us and instead exercising one&#8217;s existentialist agency in defining value where there is none to begin with.</p>

<p>And here is where I find myself getting lost over and over again, feeling discouraged and wondering whether thinking this idealistic nonsense about &#8220;what matters&#8221; is even worth my precious time. Not to mention, this kind of introspection can be incredibly uncomfortable. Looking at oneself honestly and critically takes a very unique kind of courage that takes time to develop. Reevaluating what I really care about means putting at risk the very principles that I&#8217;ve lived by, and that means admitting the possibility that I&#8217;ve been mistaken. In short, reflecting on one&#8217;s values and decisions places oneself in a most vulnerable state. Lately I&#8217;ve been asking myself questions like, What does it mean for me to feel shame at getting a low grade despite trying my hardest? Why do I measure myself relative to the academic/professional success of my peers? How come I&#8217;ve known friend X for so long but we never talk about anything beyond what&#8217;s mundane and humorous?</p>

<p>I&#8217;m guessing that many college students never reach the point of uncomfortable self-questioning and unconsciously adopt the values that are most prevalent in their culture. At Yale, these tend to be material values; high grades, an impressive resume, lots of &#8220;friends&#8221;, and a hyperactive social life. After Yale, later in life, what&#8217;s important will be professional success, reputation, a six-digit salary, and the type of decadent lifestyle that would make any onlooker envious. We&#8217;ve all encountered this type of careerist attitude. And I&#8217;m not pretending that I&#8217;m totally immune to this attitude either. There does exist a very real necessity in securing financial stability. But the importance of material success is exaggerated. I usually only ever hear mention of the following career paths: becoming a doctor, lawyer, engineer, programmer, banker, and consultant. At dinner parties, when parents ask &#8220;What&#8217;s your major?&#8221;, they&#8217;re expecting to hear something like &#8220;econ&#8221; or &#8220;computer science&#8221; or &#8220;premed&#8221;. When I say &#8220;philosophy,&#8221; they give me a strange look and they don&#8217;t know what to say to me.</p>

<p>Usually the response I get to this thought is, &#8220;Who are you to judge those who value professional success? You don&#8217;t know their financial background. They could very well be trying to improve the quality of life for their family.&#8221; But even in extreme cases my point still holds: valuing material success does not require giving up one&#8217;s more fundamental values: friendship, family, identity, etc. Material success should only ever be considered as a means to a an end, and never as an end in itself. Spending four years at a place like Yale and then many more years in the job market makes it easy to forget that principle.</p>

<p>Another result of the lack of introspective thinking is that students become unable to talk their values. Granted, sharing one&#8217;s core values isn&#8217;t something that we feel comfortable doing with just anybody. It&#8217;s one thing to refrain from talking about one&#8217;s deepest beliefs with mere acquaintances;  but what about between friends who have known each other for years? What are two long-time friends to each other if they can&#8217;t share their thoughts about what they care about? I take it that these sterile, surface-level friendships persist when neither of the two friends take the risk of talking about non-trivial matters that require exposing one&#8217;s values and emotions. These conversations can be awkward and painful, but with a true friend, they shouldn&#8217;t be.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve had the privilege of meeting some incredibly insightful and interesting students during my time here. But always, I find myself wishing that we could talk for longer and about things other than what we&#8217;re doing over the summer and how our classes are going. I find myself wishing that we were in a culture where it wasn&#8217;t socially unacceptable to bring up deeper, more personal, perhaps  more depressing issues when they&#8217;re weighing on either person&#8217;s mind and to converse honestly about them.</p>

<p>I realize that I can go on for paragraphs and paragraphs, iterating on this point indefinitely, each one digressing a little more from the next but all motivated by the same worries. It&#8217;s always a challenge for me to package thoughts on this subject into something coherent and elegant. If these questions were that easy to understand, these worries wouldn&#8217;t be eating away at me all the time.</p>

<p>The most salient point I hoped to articulate was this: creative, self-reflective, introspective thinking is immensely difficult, especially in an environment where my time and energy is nearly depleted by external responsibilities. It takes an additional strength in refusing to let one&#8217;s environment take away one&#8217;s capacity for this kind of thinking. Knowing how difficult it is at college, I need to spend more time away from all of the work and noise and distractions. I need to spend more time at the piano, more time reading, taking walks on beautiful fall days, talking to get to know someone, writing for myself; all of it as a way to step back from it all and see how far I&#8217;ve come and where I am headed.</p>

<p>And just as importantly, pursuing experiences to get to know myself and the world. Chasing those experiences that keep alive our innate sensibility to the beauty of the world, a sensibility that dulls with age and with time. Revolting against the incessant demands of practicality as a proud romantic, eyes directed toward the sublime. Because what is it all for if we can no longer dream?</p>

<div class="footnotes">
    <ol>
        <li id='fn:1'><p> <a href="http://www.freewebs.com/lanzbom/EBWhiteLakeEssay.pdf">Once More to the Lake by E.B. White</a> <br> <a href="http://web.ics.purdue.edu/~drkelly/DFWKenyonAddress2005.pdf">Kenyon Commencement Speech by David Foster Wallace</a> <br> <a href="http://www.harveyxia.com/mr-mcculloughs-2012-commencement-speech/">Wellesley High School 2012 Commencement Speech by David McCullough Jr.</a> <br> <a href="http://thoughtcatalog.com/charles-warnke/2011/01/dont-date-a-girl-who-reads/">You Should Date an Illiterate Girl by Charles Warnke</a> <br> <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/09/17/the-referendum/?_r=1">The Referendum by Tim Kreider</a> <br> <a href="http://mitadmissions.org/blogs/entry/meltdown">Meltdown by Lydia K.</a> <br>
<a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></p>
</li>
    </ol>
</div>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[My Visit to New York]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//my-visit-to-new-york"/>
		<updated>2013-09-01T15:56:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//my-visit-to-new-york</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago Caitlin and I visited New York as our last trip of the summer, a last reprieve before fall semester. We stayed at my older brother&#8217;s apartment in the Lower East Side, on Houston Street. It&#8217;s what you would expect of a New York apartment for a young professional: simple and functional decor, cramped, moderately run down, and windows overlooking dirty alleyways. The entrance to the apartment is a sketchy, non-descript metal door covered with graffiti. The first floor landing reeks of the trash from the neighboring Mexican restaurant. All this for a ridiculous rent.</p>

<p>From what I gathered, many post-college professionals like to live in neighborhoods like the Lower East Side for its nightlife. There must have been at least three or four bars every block. Weekday nights, and especially on weekends, the streets became a kalaidoscope of inebriated New Yorkers dressed in the latest hip clothing, shouting, laughing, and cursing in a hedonic riot.</p>

<p>As an underage college student from a Boston suburb, all of this was overwhelming. Being from Boston, what urban nightlife looks like isn&#8217;t completely unknown to me, but Boston, in my opinion, is a much tamer city than New York. Comparing it to New York, one can see why Boston has its nickname of &#8220;town&#8221;. Comparing New York to other cities, one can see why it frequently symbolizes a city of excess and hedonism.</p>

<p>But that was just the impression that that particular neighborhood gave me. New York&#8217;s neighborhoods are incredibly distinct, in a way that I had never experienced with Boston. We went to Chelsea, the Meatpacking District, Chinatown, Little Italy, Financial District, SoHo, Garment District, and the Upper East Side, among others. Each neighborhood has its own distinct features: its own appearance, ethnic influences, and commercial focuses. KTown has excellent, authentic Korean barbeque. The Financial District sports Wall Street and gigantic skyscrapers. The Meatpacking district smells like sewage.</p>

<p>Then there&#8217;s Central Park. I hadn&#8217;t realized until this trip just how big Central Park is. In the middle of the park there is a castle from the top of which you get an awesome view. On the east side near the Met there&#8217;s an ancient Egyptian obelisk that was given to New York as a gift from some Egyptian president. On the south side there is an area with chess boards carved into stone tables where people can challenge the local masters.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m having a hard time tying everything together and keeping myself from digressing. It&#8217;s hard for me to decide which of my experiences is essential, and which are merely tangential. But I think the truth about NYC is that there is no such experience that is only tangential. The Empire State Building and Times Square do not characterize New York to the slightest extent. I don&#8217;t claim to understand New York the same way a native New Yorker would, but from my few trips, I can see how New York&#8217;s distinct feel comes from its mosaic-like nature. Perhaps one of the only unifying New York experience is the experience of its lack of unity, its chaos and discord.</p>

<p>Another universal New York trait might be its noise. Walt Whitman wrote, &#8220;Silence? What can New York-noisy, roaring, rumbling, tumbling, bustling, story, turbulent New York-have to do with silence?&#8221; More bothersome than its light pollution is its sound pollution. There is a constant din of city sounds: loud cars, loud talking, loud contstruction.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m definitely still a Bostonian. I prefer its quieter and cleaner streets, its crooked non-grid layout, and the fact that you can see the Prudential Center from almost anywhere. I like the more manageable Boston Common with its ducks and swans, the Charles and its sailboats, the harbor beautiful in the sunset. But who knows, maybe I&#8217;ll get bored one day and decide I want to see what&#8217;s it&#8217;s like living in New York City.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Not-so-instant ramen]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//not-so-instant-ramen"/>
		<updated>2013-07-15T18:01:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//not-so-instant-ramen</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Until a few weeks ago, I thought that &#8216;ramen&#8217; referred only to that packaged stuff notorious for sustaining students through their college years. I had no idea that &#8216;instant ramen&#8217; was based off of a real Japanese dish. A friend told me about a small, locally famous ramen shop in Porter Square, Cambridge. &#8220;Give yourself some time&#8221;, she said. &#8220;You&#8217;ll be waiting in line for a while.&#8221;</p>

<p>Turns out there are two ramen shops in Porter Square, both of which are regarded as the best ramen in the Boston area. The one my friend was referring to is called &#8220;Yume Wo Katare.&#8221; The one I ended up going to is called &#8220;Sapporo Ramen.&#8221; Yume Wo Katare is closed over the summer. I guess its Japanese chef, who apparently has opened multiple restaurants in Japan, is visiting Japan.</p>

<p>Sapporo Ramen is a charming little shop hidden away in a small shopping center. It&#8217;s the size of a living room, and it&#8217;s tiny kitchen is tucked away in a corner. There are only about 7 or 8 tables, and a line usually stretches down the hallway. I have always been a big fan of instant ramen, especially the fiery Korean Shin brand. I was blown away by my first real bowl of ramen, served in a large clay bowl, filled to the brim with yellow noodles and steaming broth. Ramen looks very attractive when served with all its toppings laid out nicely. I told myself to remember to snap a picture before I dug in, but my appetite got the better of me. Caitlin reminded me, but it was too late.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/not-so-instant_ramen/sapporo_ramen.jpg" title="'Before I ate it all'" ></p>

<p>The broth, brewed with pork bones and aromatics for over 10 hours, tastes amazing — a savory and salty umami heaven. The yellow wheat noodles are what the name &#8216;ramen&#8217; refers to. They are made using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramen#Noodles">kansui</a>, a mix of sodium carbonate and potassium carbonate. The alkalinity of these two compounds keeps the noodles from becoming mushy when sitting in the hot broth and helps them maintain the chewiness that makes them so satisfying to munch on. On top of the broth and ramen, a number of toppings are placed. This <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramen#Regional_variations">depends on the style</a>. The noodles I ordered had pork, beansprouts, scallions, nori (dried seaweed), corn, and half a boied egg.</p>

<p>The ramen was so good I finished the whole bowl, including the soup. I felt bloated afterwards, but it was worth it. During another visit I ordered double the amount of noodles and finished all of it, plus the broth, plus Caitlin&#8217;s broth. Again, worth it. Besides, it&#8217;s customary in Japanese culture to finish everything on your plate.</p>

<p>We were so impressed by these noodles that Caitlin and I decided to try our hand at them. I followed this <a href="http://norecipes.com/blog/tonkotsu-ramen-recipe/#sthash.ffFEVWKz.00fOSJvo.dpbs">recipe</a>, which I highly recommend if you want to try making ramen from scratch. The recipe is for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramen#Soup">tonkotsu</a> style ramen, characterized by its creamy, fat and collagen rich pork broth. The author even has a recipe for making your own ramen noodles from scratch.</p>

<p>I have to say, making the two bowls of ramen was one of the more challenging and stressful things I&#8217;ve done. The broth itself took three hours to prepare and involved cleaning the bones and purifying the blood from them. We used a pressure cooker to speed up the process of extracting that yummy umami flavor from the bones. The chasu required about an hour of slow simmering in a rich braising liquid (miso, soy sauce, sake, mirin, cinnamon bark, star anise, sugar, etc.) In fact, most of the sauces required were ridiculously complicated, requiring a vast number of ingredients, most of which I had never heard of before. I guess that&#8217;s where the uniquely memorable flavor comes from.</p>

<p>Preparing it required a lot of attention, multitasking, and care. The details mattered, from mincing the fatback small enough that it would dissolve properly (giving the broth an added creaminess) to slicing the scallions in the right shape.</p>

<p>After two days of preparation, it was pretty satisfying to see the finished bowls.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/not-so-instant_ramen/homemade_ramen.jpg" title="'One of the greatest achievements to date'" ></p>

<p>Attention to the details is what defines great ramen, and from experience, I can say that this dish has a very high skill cap. What I mean by that is that unlike some foods (making toast, for instance), ramen can vary greatly in its quality — from great to legendary. It&#8217;s also a dish that gives the chef lots of space for innovation, both in preparation method and choice of ingredients. There are so many styles of ramen out there, and each shop has its own signature variations that define the dish.</p>

<p>I plan on traveling to Japan in the not-too-distant-future to experience first-hand its culture, history, and its world-renowned food. Hopefully it&#8217;s not too naive of me to work towards perfecting a ramen that someday I&#8217;ll get to call my own. This is the beginning of my story of ramen. May it unfold one slurp at a time.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning to cook for an epicurean]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//learning-to-cook-for-an-epicurean"/>
		<updated>2013-07-01T17:47:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//learning-to-cook-for-an-epicurean</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&#8220;The flesh receives as unlimited the limits of pleasure; and to provide it requires unlimited time. But the mind, intellectually grasping what the end and limit of the flesh is, and banishing the terrors of the future, procures a complete and perfect life, and we have no longer any need of unlimited time. Nevertheless the mind does not shun pleasure, and even when circumstances make death imminent, the mind does not lack enjoyment of the best life.&#8221;</p>

<p>— Epicurus, Principle Doctrines—</p></blockquote>

<p>I was confused when I first heard the term &#8220;epicurean&#8221; used to describe someone who pursues sensual pleasures (especially with respect to food). There is the common misconcenption that the ancient Epicureans, since they believed that pleasure is the chief Good, advocated pursuing pleasure without limitation. Epicurus actually considered freedom from fear and pain as the optimum state. This required the individual to exercise prudence and restraint, because enjoying too much of a good thing can decrease satisfaction and increase desire. So how come the name of a philosophical doctrine that preaches moderation and condemns excess is used to describe those who love gourmet food? But before I offer my thoughts on this, I&#8217;ll first talk about my new hobby.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve always been curious about cooking from a distance; on cooking shows, I would admire chefs like Gordon Ramsay and Ming Tsai artfully construct a dish whose appearance would be enough to make my mouth water. And naturally, I&#8217;m fan of good food, everything from those perfectly cooked Five Guys burgers to the amazingly authentic food of Sichuan Gourmet.</p>

<p>Only recently though, have I resolved to learn how to cook, how to <em>really</em> cook, adding it to my lifelong TODO list. Why now? I think partly it&#8217;s because during the semester I very quickly get bored of eating college food. It&#8217;s not that the food tastes bad (Yale serves great college food except for that nasty cauliflower overcooked to a paste that Berkeley sometimes makes), but that it tastes boring. After a few weeks everything tastes familiar, and not in the good homey way. It tastes familiar in the I&#8217;m-tired-of-this-same-old-shit sort of way.</p>

<p>Another reason is my lifelong obsession with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szechuan_cuisine">Sichuan gourmet</a>. Sichuan is a region in China famous for it&#8217;s ridiculously spicy-hot, flavor-packed dishes. I haven&#8217;t experienced any other type of food that matches Sichuan cuisine in terms of sheer flavor and uniqueness of taste. No other food can make me down so much rice in one meal.</p>

<p>Also, in the past year I&#8217;ve been going out to restaurants more often, sometimes to upscale places. I find myself having stronger, more polarized opinions about the food. Sometimes I will be so impressed with the food that I won&#8217;t be able to stop thinking about it, like having a song get stuck in your head. Sometimes I&#8217;ll be so severely disappointed with the food that I&#8217;ll publicly swear never to go to that restaurant again.</p>

<p>This summer I will try my inexperienced hand at the world&#8217;s various cuisines, starting with the dishes that I love. Every so often I&#8217;ll write about my successes, my failures, and what I&#8217;ve learned about the nature of taste. I&#8217;m determined to learn all the basic cooking techniques (sauteing, baking, boiling, etc), <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RjWkO9A-Ckk">how to wield a knife</a>, and how to use different ingredients. Hopefully I will also learn a thing or two about enjoying food that is prepared with such great care.</p>

<p>Viewed in this way, the Epicurean label isn&#8217;t as paradoxical as I originally thought. Fully appreciating food for its excellence isn&#8217;t as easy or instinctive as I thought. Perhaps the Epicurean would say that thoughtfully enjoying the gastronomic goodness of food is far more in the Epicurean spirit than simply gobbling it down to satiate hunger.</p>

<p>Eating can be as much an art as cooking, and cooking, I imagine, enlightens one to this art.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Silliman at Sunset]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//silliman-sunset"/>
		<updated>2013-05-04T20:43:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//silliman-sunset</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/silliman.JPG" width="700"></p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Morality: A Necessary Component of Rationality]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//morality-a-necessary-component-of-rationality"/>
		<updated>2013-05-03T23:21:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//morality-a-necessary-component-of-rationality</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>Why be moral? It’s a question that keeps philosophers up at night, perhaps even more so than questions about what morality demands. This question is difficult to answer because of the seemingly contradictory natures of morality and rationality. It seems fair to say that, regardless of its particular principles, a plausible moral theory must demand self-sacrifice of individuals. This is simply obvious. It also seems intuitive that the proper account of rationality is one that is based on self-interest. That is to say, the reasons that motivate us are ones that accord with our self-interest. This claim is more controversial and many philosophers argue that it is the wrong account of rationality. I hope to defend the account of rationality as founded on self-interest, and to offer the beginnings of a possible answer to the question “Why be moral?” within the framework that this account of rationality entails. To illustrate my point most effectively, I will argue the latter claim before the former.</p>

<p>First, let’s just assume that our rationality is based predominantly on our self-interest. How do we reconcile morality’s demand of self-sacrifice and rationality’s demand of self-interest? One might be inclined to give the Big Stick Solution (henceforth, BSS): it is rational to be moral because the individual will be punished if he cheats the moral system. Since it is not in his self-interest to be punished, he must adhere to the moral system. This solution relies on the assumption that there exists an omniscient and omnipotent enforcer who has the power to both perfectly know and punish those who cheat the system. The legal system of a society might be such an enforcer. For instance, society punishes individuals who commit murder by taking their freedom taken away and placing them in prison. Even ignoring practical questions of the possibility of an adequate enforcement, there is a significant problem with this approach: it subordinates morality to self-interest and defines self-interest in terms of personal well-being. The solution suggests that morality should only be valued insofar as it affects our personal well-being. People shouldn’t commit murder because they will get caught and punished. This account of morality seems obviously false because morality should be valued in and of itself. In other words, morality should considered as an end, not simply as a means to promoting our well being. Given that the BSS relies on an account of morality that is so implausible, it does not give us the best answer for the question “Why be moral?”</p>

<p>The BSS also employs the wrong account of human rationality for two reasons. The first reason is that it defines our self-interest negatively by claiming that humans desire not to be punished. It is insufficient to portray our rationality in terms of what we want to avoid. Of course we want to avoid physical and emotional harm, but our rationality strives for more than just ensuring our safety against what we fear. I acknowledge that nevertheless, avoiding harm is indeed a goal of rationality. But in answering the question, “Why be moral”, we must look at the complete account of rationality. Morality does not only relate to rationality through the one desire to avoid punishment. Our rationality gives us both long and short term ends that we pursue in order to better our lives. It seems better to define our rationality positively, in terms of striving to live the best life possible and fulfilling the goals that rationality determines. Thus, in discussing the relationship between morality and rationality, morality does not simply matter insofar as the failure to obey its rules might bring us harm. To give a satisfying account of why acting morally is also acting rationally, morality must be discussed as it pertains to fulfilling the goals that our rationality sets.</p>

<p>As I mentioned before, the BSS makes the mistake of defining self-interest solely in terms of well-being. For the BSS theorist, what’s in our self-interest is what promotes our own well-being. Thus, the problem of treating morality merely a means arises because this view commits the BSS theorist to value morality only insofar as morality affects well-being. But self-interest is clearly not the same as well-being. An action can promote my self-interest but be harmful to my well-being. Conversely, something can promote my well-being without promoting my self-interest. For instance, I can choose to donate one of my kidneys to my brother. This would be in my self-interest because I care about my brother’s health, but it would not be promoting my well-being because I am giving away my organ. The concept of self-interest can be explained more coherently by basing it on rational desires. A rational desire is a desire that is based on the reasons available to the individual at that time. A psychopathic desire to murder people is not a rational desire. A desire to donate one’s kidney to save a family member is a rational desire. What’s in my self-interest is what fulfills my rational desires.</p>

<p>If it is in one’s self-interest to act according to their rational desires, then a simpler solution to the moral question emerges. Why be moral? Because we have the rational desire to be moral, and it is in our rational self-interest to fulfill these desires. One’s first impression might be that this solution is circular: we should be moral because we should be moral. But this is misunderstanding the logic; we should be moral because we rationally want to be moral. Of course it could be objected that not everybody has the rational desire to be moral, that some people abhor morality and consciously act against its principles. Recall, however, that the BSS was inadequate because it treated morality as a means rather than an end. This was enough for us to reject the BSS because intuitively, we believe that obeying morality has intrinsic value. This very intuition shows us that most of us have the desire to be moral, regardless of what the content of the moral system are. Insofar as we have the rational desire to be moral and that to act rationally with regard to our self-interest means to act in way that promotes the realization of these rational desires, we should be moral. This solution offers a way to reconcile the seemingly contrary demands of morality and of rationality, while allowing us to preserve the self-interested account of rationality.</p>

<p>What about the individual who has no desire to be moral? It seems unlikely that we can both maintain our notion of morality as having intrinsic value and find reasons that motivate him to be moral. If he does not have the desire to be moral, then acting morally for the sake of acting morally cannot be in his self-interest. For such a person, it seems that the best we can do is to revert back to the BSS, and treat morality as a means for promoting his other self-interests, most of which perhaps connect with his well-being. This way, at least we can convince him to carry out the moral actions even though he will be doing them for the wrong reasons (through purely selfish motivations).</p>

<p>Now I turn to the question of our rationality. What is the correct account of human rationality? Someone might look at the simple solution I proposed and object that it is unlikely that human self-interests include the desire to promote the well-being of others. After all, the rational interests in question are self-interests, not others’¬-interests. But this is to confuse self-interest with selfishness. As I explained above, what’s in one’s self-interest does not simply consist of what promotes one’s own well-being. Similarly, what’s in one’s self-interest does not simply consist of selfish desires. It can very well be in one’s self-interest to devote the greater part of his life to raising and caring for his children, even though doing so would involve sacrificing a significant amount of his own time, energy, and money. Self-sacrifice for others can be, and often is, an essential aspect of one’s self-interest.</p>

<p>Again, skeptics of this account of rationality might say, “By this account, the only thing I want is what’s in my self-interest. This is just obviously wrong.” But this is not the self-interested account of rationality that I put forth. The account I put forth claims that the only thing in one’s self-interest is what one wants. That is, what one’s self-interest consists of is necessarily and sufficiently explained by what one wants, which consist of the reasons one has to want something. This is the correct way to understand the self-interested account of rationality.</p>

<p>The best objection one might raise to the arguments I’ve put forth is that, “Surely the moral desire is only one of many conflicting desires an individual possesses at any point in time. Why should he choose to follow the moral desire rather than other, perhaps more selfish, desires?” This objection would be relevant for other accounts of rationality as well. If what’s rational is determined both by selfish concerns for one’s own well-being and altruistic concerns for the well-being of others, there will be conflicting desires. Why should the individual choose to act with regard to the self-interest of others over his own? Why should the individual choose to follow his moral desire? Regardless of what theory of rationality we believe, further arguments must be made to show why it is rational that the moral desire should take precedence over other desires. This is the great difficulty of moral philosophy, to construct an argument defending this normative claim and to show the validity of its normative force.</p>

<p>I did not discuss this question here, and by no means do I pretend to have fully answered the initial question, “Why be moral?” But I hope I have shown how such an answer is possible given the self-interested account of rationality, and why such an account of rationality is plausible. Unlike the Big Stick Solution, my argument does not rely on the existence of an omnipotent and omniscient enforcer. My argument relies only on the reasonable assumption that people have the desire to be moral. And from this we can see that it is rational to be moral because we have the desire to do so.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Insufficiency of Kant’s Universal Law Formulation]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-insufficiency-of-kants-universal-law-formulation"/>
		<updated>2013-04-25T12:06:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-insufficiency-of-kants-universal-law-formulation</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>The Universal Law Formulation of Kant’s Categorical Imperative states, “Act only on that maxim through which you can at the same time will that it should become a universal law” (88). Regarding the nature of the ULF Kant asserts, “…there remains nothing over to which the maxim has to conform except the universality of a law as such; and it is this conformity alone that the imperative properly asserts to be necessary” (88). Here Kant makes explicit the idea his ethical system uses universability through reason as the single necessary and sufficient condition for moral evaluation. If a maxim (a general ethical principle put into first-person terms) can be rationally willed by the individual to be universalized and shared by every rational being in the world, then the maxim and its related action are morally permissible. I will argue that universability through reason alone does not provide sufficient conditions for evaluating the morality of maxims by showing how the proper application of ULF can yield two conflicting morally obligatory answers. By morally obligatory (and I will illustrate this concept in more detail below), I mean an action that must be carried out and for which it is immoral not to. If such is possible, Kant’s moral theory is shown to be inadequate because a plausible moral theory must give non-conflicting answers.</p>

<p>Under Kant’s moral system, evaluating the morality of an action involves subjecting it to this test of universability, which I will call the ULF test. A maxim can fail the test in two ways: it can give rise to a contradiction in conception or a contradiction in willing. Contradiction in conception occurs when it is impossible to even conceive of a world in which the given maxim is universalized. Contradiction in willing occurs when the individual finds himself worse off in a where the given maxim is universalized, and so cannot will it to be universal. For a maxim to pass the test, it must have neither contradiction. For an action to be morally permissible, its maxim must pass the test. For an action to be morally obligatory, all the maxims permitting the failure of carrying out that action must fail the ULF test. Conversely, for an action to be morally forbidden, all the maxims permitting that action must fail.</p>

<p>Consider the following scenario: a paramedic on the scene of a car accident. The car drove off a bridge and fell into a river. The driver of the car could not escape the car and drowned. Upon examining the body, the paramedic concludes that the driver did not die instantly, but drowned while struggling desperately to escape. When the driver’s wife arrives on the scene of the accident, she asks the paramedic if her husband died quickly or suffered before his death. What should the paramedic tell her?</p>

<p>The ULF test can yield the answer that it is morally obligatory to tell the wife the truth. Every maxim that permits lying to the wife contradicts itself in conception because in a world where every paramedic simply told the story that is easier for the wife to bear (that the victim died painlessly), there would be no point to even asking the paramedic in the first place. In such a world, the victim’s wife would know that the paramedic always gives this answer, regardless of the truth, so they would see no point in asking. Furthermore, there seems to be a contradiction in willing for maxims which permit lying in these cases. Could the paramedic really will that all paramedics in this position lie? Then, if the paramedic were to find himself in the position of the wife, he would never know the truth about the victim’s death. Surely he cannot will that he himself might be placed in such an undesirable situation. On the other hand, maxims that permit telling the truth all pass the ULF test. There is no contradiction in conception because wives would continue to ask paramedics for the true account of how the victim died. There is no contradiction in will because if the paramedic were placed in such a situation, he would want to know that the story the paramedic tells him is in fact true. The honest paramedic would argue that it is morally obligatory to tell the truth because all maxims permitting lying in this scenario would fail because they rise to both contradictions in conception and will.</p>

<p>However, the ULF test can also yield the answer that it is morally obligatory to lie to the wife. In response to the arguments above that a lie-permitting maxim would generate a contradiction in conception, the dishonest paramedic could argue that such a contradiction only arises if the paramedic’s sole duty is to tell the truth. He might argue that while telling the truth is one possible purpose, the greater purpose is to lessen the emotional trauma of the victim’s wife. If this latter purpose has been established as a premise, then there is no contradiction in conception because the paramedic would still have a purpose answering the wife, which is to reduce her emotional suffering. While the honest paramedic might rebut by pointing out that in a world where this maxim is universalized, the wife would know that the paramedic only ever gives the easier account, and so their emotional trauma would not be lessened because they would still left in uncertainty about what happened. But even so, for the wife, there still exists a 50% chance that her husband actually died painlessly according to the paramedic. If the paramedic always told the truth, then the wife either knows 100% that the husband died painfully or painlessly. By eliminating the possibility that the wife knows for certain her husband died painfully, the wife is better off emotionally. This is resting on the assumption that, for anyone in the wife’s situation, the emotional suffering that would occur from knowing the worse outcome greatly outbalances the peace of mind from knowing the better outcome. As for contradiction in willing, the dishonest paramedic agrees with the above assumption and would rather be left uncertain than chance knowing the worse outcome. Thus, the dishonest paramedic can reasonably will this maxim to be universal. More importantly, he would argue that giving the easier account is morally obligatory because all maxims permitting the paramedic to tell the truth in the case where the victim died painfully would fail the ULF test. Given that the duty of the paramedic is to reduce the emotional trauma of the already suffering wife, he must give the easier answer. A contradiction in willing arises otherwise, because the honest paramedic could not will himself to be in a situation where he is at danger for suffering the additional emotional weight of knowing the victim died painfully.</p>

<p>The ULF test seems to yield two conflicting answers, that it is morally obligatory to tell the truth and that it is morally obligatory to lie and give the easier answer. Why do the two paramedics reach opposite conclusions while properly applying the ULF test?</p>

<p>This problem, as I see it, arises because the ULF does not contain enough content to yield clear and non-conflicting moral answers. Because both views are supported by reason and both pass the ULF test as obligatory, universability through reason is shown to be insufficient to yield a single moral answer, and thus insufficient as the sole condition of an ethical system. There is a missing ingredient that differentiates why an individual would choose one position over the other. The issue is put into focus in examining how each side argues that the other side leads to contradictions in willing. The honest paramedic believes that no rational individual in this situation would will themselves into a position where he would be lied to, while the dishonest paramedic believes that no rational individual in this position would will themselves into a more emotionally vulnerable position. It seems that the two paramedics value different things in this situation: the honest paramedic values knowing the truth and the dishonest paramedic values peace of mind. It is the paramedics’ different values that cause them to make opposite conclusions. A plausible moral theory must include a mechanism that allows the individual to establish the relative importance of values in any given moral dilemma. As illustrated by the paramedic example, mere universability fails to do this. It seems perfectly reasonable to me that an individual can will a world where everybody in the paramedic scenario values knowing the truth, or that he wills a world where everybody values avoiding further emotional stress. Both of these values can be universalized through reason.</p>

<p>The Kantian might contend reason is sufficient to determine what values are most important. He might argue that truth is obviously more valuable than emotional comfort because the successful function of rationality depends on understanding of the truth. Because rationality guides our actions and helps us make the best decisions, it is in everybody’s best interest to maximize the access they have to reality. While this argument might hold true if we are talking about the scope of one’s lifetime, it does not, I think, hold for the isolated paramedic case. If I stipulate that the wife’s knowing or not knowing the truth is inconsequential with respect to her future rational decisions, then the argument that truth is more valuable falls apart. I acknowledge that I have sketched a consequentialist argument for the value of truth and that there are other ways of arguing for truth’s value. However, I think the consequentialist argument for truth is the strongest insofar as we are discussing the application of the ULF because it is most likely to be universalized. It is harder to universalize a value based on a belief in its intrinsic importance, because other individuals might not share that belief. The Kantian might still argue that the perfect use of reason is sufficient to yield this hierarchy of values. But since I have never seen this successfully demonstrated, I remain unconvinced. It seems then, that the application of reason alone leaves room for valuing both truth and emotional comfort, but provides no way of choosing between the two. Keep in mind that one of the two values must take precedence in this case of two conflicting morally obligatory answers in which the ULF has been applied properly in both positions.</p>

<p>It would be beyond the scope of this paper to introduce a plausible mechanism for deciding the relative importance of values in cases like these. I hope I have shown that Kant’s ULF, which contains universability through reason as its only condition for moral evaluation, is insufficient. In conceiving of the ULF, Kant seems to have overextended the powers of reason far beyond what is plausible for an ethical theory. Although I realize that a discussion about the nature of reason itself would require much detail than what I can offer here, I will nevertheless venture to make some remarks about reason as they relate to the shortcomings of Kant’s moral theory. Reason is most effective as an evaluative instrument given the initial premises. It cannot, however, be relied on alone to generate fundamental premises for a moral theory, let alone plausibly universal premises. Even the perfect use of reason cannot do this. Thus, individuals properly applying reason will arrive at different moral conclusions if they have different premises or moral values. The nature of reason is different than what Kant thought, and the ULF must be amended to include a way for individuals with different values to rationally evaluate the importance of their own values relative to other values in a given moral dilemma, with the goal of arriving at a definitive moral answer. Although the question remains open as to whether or not any moral system can fully achieve this goal, Kant’s ULF can without a doubt be improved in this respect.</p>

<p>Works Cited</p>

<p>Kant, Immanuel. Ground of the Metaphysics of Morals. Trans. H.J. Paton. New York: Harper    Perennial, 2009.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Assertions: Updating the Context Set]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//assertions-updating-the-context-set"/>
		<updated>2013-04-24T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//assertions-updating-the-context-set</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>In his article <a href="http://www.princeton.edu/~harman/Courses/PHI534-2012-13/Lepore/stalnaker78.pdf">“Assertion&#8221;</a>, Stalnaker gives a pragmatic account of the function of assertions in language. He states that assertions, when not rejected by other conversational participants, serve to reduce the context set of the conversation. Stalnaker uses the term ‘context set’ to refer to the set of all possible worlds that are compatible with the presuppositions of the speaker. For instance, in a conversation about upcoming weekend plans, the context set cannot include possible worlds where the speaker is talking with the philosopher Kant because such worlds do not accord with the presupposition that Kant is dead. Assertions reduce the context set by taking into account the content represented by the proposition asserted to the existing presuppositions. Increasing the number of things presupposed will necessarily lead to a reduction in the context set because the addition of new presuppositions rules out worlds incompatible with the proposition. For Stalnaker, a proposition is a “representation of the world as being a certain way,” and so determines a set of possible worlds. So another way of thinking about Stalnaker’s account of assertions is that when assertions are made, the intersection of the existing context set and the set of possible worlds represented by the proposition becomes the new context set. I will argue, however, that assertions can also function to broaden the context set. If this is true, then assertions function to update the context set rather than just restricting it, contrary to Stalnaker’s account.</p>

<p>Stalnaker states that he does not offer this account as a sufficient definition of assertion, but rather as one component of an adequate definition. Although he makes some remarks about the reason why assertions cannot be sufficiently defined by this effect alone, he does not mention anything about assertions being able to broaden the context set. It seems to me that such assertions occur regularly, even in “non-nondefective” conversations where the speakers initially presuppose the same things. If assertions can in fact broaden the context, Stalnaker’s account of this particular function of assertions is inadequate.</p>

<p>Suppose two friends are deciding on what type of restaurant to go to. They typically prefer pizza and have only ever been to pizza restaurants. One of them asks, “What pizza place do you want to go to?” On this particular day, however, the other replies, “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place,” and the other agrees. The initial context set only included worlds where the two are eating at pizza restaurants. It seems that the new context set includes worlds where the two are eating at restaurants that both serve pizza and do not (assuming that the speaker did not mean to rule out possible worlds where the two still went to a pizza restaurant).</p>

<p>But there arises a problem. What is semantically expressed by propositions of the form, “It might be that,” or “It could be that,” turns out to be either necessarily true or necessarily false for all the worlds in the context set. The semantic content of “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place” is that there is some world Φ in the context set in which the two are not eating at a pizza place. In the existing context set, there either is a world Φ or there isn’t. If Φ does exist in the context set, then for every possible world in the context set, the proposition is true.  But in the pizza case, since it was presupposed by both speakers that they would eat at a pizza place, the world Φ is not in the context set. Therefore, the statement “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place” is necessarily false relative to every possible world in the context set.</p>

<p>This violates the principle that Stalnaker takes to be a necessary for rational communication: a proposition asserted must be true in some but not all of the possible worlds in the context set. This principle seems obvious because otherwise the proposition expressed would not be advancing the conversation in any way since it is either trivially true or trivially false. If we assume that the speaker is rational and intends on engaging in a genuine conversation, it seems wrong to interpret his statement as asserting a proposition that is trivially false. Something else seems to be happening. Thus, the fact that the statement is trivially false triggers a pragmatic, Gricean reinterpretation. The speaker wishes to communicate something other than what is literally asserted by the utterance. Given that the statement is false at all possible worlds in the context set, it seems that the speaker wishes to broaden the context set to include possible worlds in which the two are not eating at a pizza place. I will explain how this is possible.</p>

<p>If the other speaker agrees, the context set is broadened to now include the world(s) Φ where they are not eating at a pizza place. Consequently, what’s true for the worlds in the context set has changed. Now, there are worlds for which it is possible that the two might eat at a non-pizza place. The new context set is the result of the union of the previous context set and the set of possible worlds represented by the asserted proposition. But once the context set is updated to include world Φ, there remains the problem that now the statement is trivially true. One solution to this problem is that what is possible at each of the possible worlds is different. At some set of worlds in the context set, it is possible that they will eat at a pizza place. At some other set of worlds in the context set, it is possible that they will eat at a non-pizza place. I offer this only as a mere gesture towards what an adequate solution may be. For the purposes of this paper, I assume that such a solution is possible. The exact details of that solution are not critical to my argument.</p>

<p>The statement is no longer trivially false because it accords with the principle that the proposition asserted is true in some but not all of the worlds in the context set. The speaker has successfully advanced the conversation by broadening the context set. This claim runs contrary to Stalnaker’s notion that the new context set is the result of the intersection of the existing context set and the set of worlds represented by the proposition asserted. I see no reason why the context set cannot be changed by either the intersection or the union of itself with an asserted proposition, depending on whether the assertion is intended to restrict or broaden the context set, respectively. It seems more accurate to say that conversations are advanced when the context set is updated in some way, rather than only restricted.</p>

<p>Statements of the form “It might be the case that…” or “It could be the case that…” often signal an assertion that broadens the context set. One might argue that such statements are not assertions, but some other linguistic move that functions differently. These sorts of utterances, however, do seem to be assertions. When he says “We might eat somewhere other than a pizza place” he is really asserting the proposition that represents the set of worlds in which the two are eating at a non-pizza restaurant, along with expressing his desire that the other speaker accept this assertion.</p>

<p>Philosophical skeptics often make these statements. If a skeptic utters, “We could be experiencing a dream right now,” he is asserting the proposition that represents the worlds in which the speaker is dreaming. It would be unfair to think that skeptical utterances cannot be assertions; certain types of skeptical utterances, especially philosophical ones, aim expressly to break down certain presuppositions, opening up new possible worlds to consider in the discussion.</p>

<p>To defend this claim of mine, it is important to consider why Stalnaker thinks of assertions as functioning solely to restrict the context set. Stalnaker accounts for assertions in this way because the point of a conversation (or at least, the type of conversation in which assertions are employed) is to locate the actual world that the speakers are in. By restricting the context set and limiting the set of possible worlds as live options, the speakers hope to eventually reach a point where only one possible world remains, that one being the real world. Of course, this is only a brief sketch of what actually happens. Different conversations would require different degrees of certainty; a conversation centered on diagnosing a patient would demand that only a single world be left as a live option, so that the doctors know exactly how to treat him. In a conversation about a sports game between two speakers who don’t particular care about sports, the speakers would be satisfied with a number of possible worlds as live options (“The Celtics won, but the final score was either 98-78 or 99-76”).</p>

<p>Given the goal of locating the actual world within the context set, it very well might be the case that a mistake was made by the speakers and the actual world was ruled out by certain false presuppositions. If, as Stalnaker suggests, the role of assertions is to locate the actual world, then it seems perfectly justified, perhaps even necessary, that assertions also function to broaden the context set in such situations. As mentioned above, Cartesian philosophical skeptics make certain statements to account for the possibility that the world is just an illusion orchestrated by an evil demon. Since they are aiming to uncover a metaphysical truth (attempting to locate the real world within the context set), the skeptics are indeed making assertions.</p>

<p>Perhaps another example will make this point clearer. Consider a murder investigation. Two detectives are examining the crime scene and debating possible suspects given the available evidence. They suspect that either the maid or the wife committed the murder, and so the context set contains the possible worlds where the maid or wife committed the crime. Suddenly one of the detectives receives a phone call from an informant telling him that there is strong evidence implicating the butler. This detective then utters, “The butler could have done it.” It is perfectly reasonable to interpret this statement as asserting the proposition that represents the possible worlds in which the butler committed the murder, thus expanding the context set (because otherwise the assertion would be trivially false, violating one of basic conversational principles regarding assertions). After all, the detectives are there to find out who killed the victim. If evidence arises implicating the butler, it seems logically necessary to expand the context set to include worlds in which the butler is the murderer, if the actual world is to be accurately located.</p>

<p>It is not a justified defense to claim that statements that broaden the context set are not assertions. Statements that broaden the context set have the same purpose that Stalnaker suggests for assertions that reduce the context set — to update the context set in hopes of locating the actual world. If the speaker’s hold a mistaken presupposition and the actual world is not within the current context set, it is necessary to broaden the context set to contain the set possible worlds where the real world might be located. Given that locating the real world is the purpose for making assertions, it is insufficient to account for assertions as only reducing the context set. The essential function of assertions seems to be that they update the context set, both by restricting and by expanding it. </p>

<p>Works Cited</p>

<ol>
<li>Robert Stalnaker, “Assertion,” Syntax and Semantics, ed. J. Kimball. Vol. 9, 1978 Academic   Press (New York), pp. 315-332.</li>
</ol>

]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress and the Hacker Aesthetic]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//octopress-and-the-hacker-aesthetic"/>
		<updated>2013-04-23T12:23:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//octopress-and-the-hacker-aesthetic</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve migrated my website from Wordpress to Octopress. Octopress has a much cleaner underlying code structure, which makes it easy for me to customize how I want my website to look and function. The only catch is that implementing these customizations is much more technical than in Wordpress; everything is done throug the command line, and there is no user-friendly GUI to help you out.</p>

<p>But this difficulty is less a hassle for me than it is a fun challenge. My interest in programming and web development/design has really taken over my semester. I&#8217;m currently learning Ruby on Rails, which also entails that I improve my facility with HTML and CSS. I plan on getting started learning Javascript (and jQuery and Coffeescript) as soon as I can.</p>

<p>Wikipedia defines Hacker as such; &#8220;In home and hobby circles, a hacker is a person who enjoys exploring the limits of what is possible, in a spirit of playful cleverness. They may also heavily modify software or hardware of their own computer system.&#8221;</p>

<p>I certainly love breaking things and customizing them to make them my own, but something about what I call the Hacker Aesthetic also appeals to me. Computer programmers have this principle DRY: Don&#8217;t Repeat Yourself. Every effort is made to streamline code by eliminating redundancy and achieving the desired outcome in the most efficient way possible. In a sense, it&#8217;s the technical manifestation of the artistic concept of minimalism, something that I value in music. All of my favorite musicians/composers have minimalist tendencies: Miles Davis, Brad Mehldau, Robert Glasper, just to name a few epitomical examples.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most tangible examples of the Hacker Aesthetic are modern websites. These sites use modern coding techniques to create fast, clean, and elegant websites both in appearance and function. Check out <a href="http://artsy.net/">artsy</a>, <a href="https://www.tumblr.com/">tumblr</a>, and <a href="http://origami.co/">origami</a>.</p>

<p>Less obvious to people who haven&#8217;t had experience with programming is the simple fact that well written code just looks good. This is what my text editor looks like with code.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.harveyxia.com//images/code.png" width="500"></p>

<p>So for now, the plan is to keep exploring computer programming and, along the way, enjoy the beauty of the Hacker&#8217;s Aesthetic.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Mental State Theory: An Inadequate Picture of Happiness]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness"/>
		<updated>2013-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>In investigating questions of human happiness, it’s important to explore the very concept of happiness itself. Unfortunately, this word is used in myriad contexts and comes loaded with many meanings. For the purposes of this article, I will use the term to refer to the deeper type of happiness that we associate with human flourishing — the type of happiness we mean when we ask ourselves the question, “Am I <em>really</em> happy?”</p>

<p>Questioning this type of happiness itself will hopefully bring into focus a better picture of the nature of happiness and its role in human flourishing, as well as introduce important questions that must be addressed in giving an adequate account of happiness. Though I acknowledge the fact that happiness has an inescapably subjective nature — after all, each of us is made happy by different things — I think we can still hold meaningful discussions about the objective aspects of happiness, namely, what it is that we think happiness <em>consists</em>.</p>

<p>Instead of attempting to answer this question directly (which would require much more than one article), I will dispute the common belief that happiness only consists of mental states, or that to be happy means to be in a certain psychological state. This particular conception of happiness is widespread. Popular moral theories, including many (although not all) variants of Utilitarianism, rest on the idea that what humans desire are positive mental states, or pleasure. Furthermore, it seems to me that in our every day lives, our default intuition seems to support decisions that maximize the pleasure of ourselves or others. It requires deeper reflection to <em>override</em> this default concern for mental states for the sake of some other value. A common example of this is when somebody accepts that they have done something wrong — his initial instinct is not to admit his fault, for that would invoke feelings of shame and guilt. But upon further reflection, he realizes that the better action is to apologize and recognize his fault for whatever reason (so that he can avoid making the same mistake next time, or that he can become a better person, etc.).</p>

<p>In challenging this simple and compelling notion of happiness as purely a psychological state, the philosopher Robert Nozick employed a well-known thought experiment known as “The Experience Machine.” Imagine sometime in the future in which human beings have the technology and the understanding of neurophysiology to construct a machine that can perfectly produce any psychological state. Once plugged in, the individual’s thoughts and beliefs can be altered in any way — he can be made to think that he is the greatest writer in the world, the greatest musician, the most wealthy, the best looking, the most popular, the most well-liked, etc. He can be made to believe, and more importantly <em>feel as if</em>, his life is perfect in every aspect; his days would be filled with nothing but elation and contentment. Assume that, while in the Experience Machine, the individual believes everything he is experiencing is real, i.e., he is not aware of being in an experience machine, and further, has no memory of being plugged in.</p>

<p>Would you plug in? Nozick believed that most people would say no, especially when given enough time to think about it. This intuitive answer does not cohere with the view that happiness is constituted only by mental states. The Experience Machine can give us the best mental states imaginable, so why would we (or at least most of us) turn down the chance to plug in?</p>

<p>A common response in defense of mental state theories is that the thought experiment is too removed from our reality. The thought experiment is too abstract, or perhaps just too foreign, for us to consider and thus cannot yield any real insight into what we think of as happiness. But this thought experiment is not as far from reality as we think. Consider alcohol or recreational drugs. People consume these substances in order to make themselves feel a certain way. But because of the damaging side effects, many people do not think the experience worth it. Is it so hard to imagine a type of drug that exaggerates the effects of, for example, heroin, and does not have any negative side effects? If not, then it seems that at least a crude version of the experience machine is not so far from our reality, after all.</p>

<p>If this answer still isn’t satisfactory, consider the following alternative scenario, which is not only possible, but happens in some form or another quite regularly: Imagine someone who is happily married to a wife whom he loves more than anything. He genuinely believes that his wife loves him in the same way, but in reality, she doesn’t love him at all. In reality, she is cheating on him and can put on a perfect act to make her husband believe the contrary. Should we say that the husband is truly happy, in the sense of <em>flourishing</em>? Is that the kind of “happiness” you would want for yourself? Put another way, if we compare two men, both of whom believe that they are loved by their wives, but only one of who actually is, would we say that they are equally well off? Or does the one with a truly loving wife have greater claim to being <em>truly</em> “happy”?</p>

<p>Having established that the Experience Machine (or the alternative experiment) is valuable to use as a thought experiment, I return to the question of why our intuition tells us to reject the offer to plug in to the machine. The answer is simple: we believe that happiness is more than just a psychological state. We value something else beyond simply experiencing certain emotions and believing certain things — we value <em>actually accomplishing</em> the things we think we are accomplishing and <em>actually being</em> the person we think we are. Striving to do things and to become a certain person seems completely meaningless if it all takes place in our heads. We pity the beguiled husband even though he believes that he is in a perfect marriage, because in reality, the marriage is broken. However, this position does not commit us to saying that mental states play <em>no</em> role in happiness. Rather, the claim I wish to advance is that mental states do not play the <em>only</em> role in happiness.</p>

<p>The question remains: What else do we value in our happiness? What else <em>should</em> we value in happiness? The question seem closely connected to what we <em>value </em> in that, what we value gives us a framework for evaluating whether or not any given individual is truly happy, and further, for determining how to live our lives in pursuit of happiness. For instance, someone who values that his life be grounded in reality and not some imaginary virtual machine will not think consider life in the Experience Machine to be one of genuine happiness.</p>

<p>After hearing these arguments, some may still want to plug in. If I asked these individuals to compare the <em>same</em> life in the experience machine, and the same life outside of the experience machine, however, I suspect most of them would regard the life outside the machine as “better” in some way. In this paper I have not argued <em>why</em> life outside the experience machine is the better alternative, or, more generally, why happiness <em>should</em> <em>not</em> consist only of mental states. This would involve a discussion of what we value and find meaningful. In this article, I hope to have at least shown that for most of us, who <em>do</em> have the intuition to refuse the experience machine, mental states are clearly not enough. Perhaps actual success or the actual possession of goods like truth, love, beauty, dignity, and freedom are intrinsically valuable and thus play a role in happiness.</p>

<p><em>Originally published in Flourish, Yale’s Undergraduate Journal for the Interdisciplinary Study of Human Flourishing</em></p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Brad Mehldau&#8217;s &#8220;My Favorite Things&#8221;]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//brad-mehldaus-my-favorite-things"/>
		<updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//brad-mehldaus-my-favorite-things</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Jazz musicians and educators always make comparisons between jazz improvisation and language. They talk of expanding one’s “jazz vocabulary” and “pacing” one’s solos effectively. They say that the best solos “tell a story.” In this way, the jazz soloist is analogous a rhetorician giving an improvised speech, attempting saying something meaningful to the audience. But sometimes, as is often the case with many of my favorite recordings, the artist seems engage in a soliloquy, full of introverted reflections. To name off the top of my head some musicians who do this a lot — Miles Davis, Wes Montgomery, and Bill Evans.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><img src="http://i.ytimg.com/vi/gClg7L_vqes/0.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>Brad Mehldau’s live recording of “My Favorite Things” is one such recording, and it’s one that means a lot to me both aesthetically and philosophically: the music itself simply sounds beautiful, and the emotions and thoughts it invokes in me are profound. Here is a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X7fVnvJSRb4">link</a> to the piece.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/joseph-vella/brad-mehldau-the-art-of-s_b_823026.html">interview</a> with the Huffington Post, Mehldau said:</p>

<blockquote><p>“One fun surprise of this concert was “My Favorite Things.” It was not something I had played before – the Coltrane version is sacred to me. But I was going out for an encore and thought of it at the last moment, and it turned out to be for me anyways, one of the more compelling performances in the set – it had that story to it; it just kind of unfolded. Sometimes you find that and sometimes you don’t; sometimes you find it with no preparation or context at all and those moments are always great for me.”</p></blockquote>

<p>The piece seems even more impressive considering that it was spontaneous. But I guess you can hear that in the recording, how it progresses so naturally from a simple introduction to a compelling climax down to an ending. The recording really does sound like a soliloquy. We seem to be hearing the depths of Mehldau’s consciousness expressed musically. You know, those deep thoughts that exist but remain unknown to us until, in solitude, they gradually become lucid. This happens to me a lot during walks in quiet, peaceful places. For artists, I would imagine it happens during those rare instances of perfect artistic inspiration.</p>

<p>I listen to this piece a lot when I’m feeling melancholic, introverted, thoughtful, nostalgic, or any other feeling that would make me temporarily anti-social and weird. Anyhow, I thought I’d share this piece. Hopefully you hear something in it that you can relate to.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Music as Sound, Sound as Music]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//music-as-sound-sound-as-music"/>
		<updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>http://www.harveyxia.com//music-as-sound-sound-as-music</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Leaning forward in my chair, I gripped my saxophone in anticipation. It was my first rehearsal with the Senior Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, the first musical group to ever intimidate me with its degree of talent and level of perfection. Widely regarded as one of the top wind ensembles in the world, the group is led by Michael Mucci — a conductor, educator, and mentor whom I admire deeply. During his opening remarks he said a curious thing.</p>

<p>“You are all here because you love sound.”</p>

<p>Strange, I thought. Why would he use the word sound? In my mind, the word “sound” stood uncomfortable close to “noise.” I wasn’t just producing mere sounds; I was making music — an art that requires skill and refinement, an art that is the opposite of noise. But for some reason, his words remained in the back of my mind and their meaning grew clearer as I matured musically through my high school years. Before this, however, I had to learn that listening to music is just as much a craft as making music.I didn’t always know how to listen to music well, and I still have a lot to learn. I remember how teachers would recommend that I listen to recordings like Miles Davis’ Kind of Blue and John Coltrane’s A Love Supreme, and how I would get bored after a few minutes. I thought it was because I didn’t understand the music theory underlying the jazz. But after devoting much time to learning about chord progressions and two-fives and secondary dominants, I still could not enjoy these records. Understanding that the tune “So What” has a modal structure that modulates up a half step in the bridge did not help me at all in appreciating the track.</p>

<p>Eventually, I was introduced to the concept of tone. Teachers emphasized the importance of developing a unique sound, asking me questions like “How would you describe your sound?” Dark, rounded, and pure, I would say. I knew that good tone was an important aspect of musicianship, but I hadn’t thought about it as something up to the musician to define. Miles Davis was always championed as having the quintessentially unique voice, so I began paying more attention to the way his trumpet sounded, not just the notes he played. With this attitude of listening for how things sounded holistically rather than how the notes were arranged, I gave Kind of Blue another shot. This time, I found myself able to sit through the full nine minutes of each track with a sustained interest. Instead of fixating on that particular bluesy lick that Cannonball played or the pentatonic scale that Coltrane used, I focused on how the richness of Bill Evan’s chords complemented Miles’ subdued tone. I noticed the contrast between the distinct sounds of Coltrane, Cannonball, and Miles, and how that lent the album a mosaic-like quality. I absorbed the recording’s general chilled, quiet, impressionistic ethos. I could go on about what I love about the album, but the point is that a simple shift in my listener’s attitude was all that I needed to understand the music. Studying jazz theory was unnecessary because listening to music involves something much more fundamental — it involves the skill of listening to sound.</p>

<p>I approached both new and familiar pieces of music with this new philosophy, asking the question: What kinds of sounds are these artists attempting to create? Sound, of course, gets conveyed in many different forms. In jazz, for example, the artist’s phrasing, tone, dynamics, intonation, rhythmic and melodic choices all characterize his sound. In classical, the composer’s orchestration and compositional choices as well as the performer’s interpretive choices comprise the sound. With this attitude, I listened with more focus; with more attention to subtle nuances and with more awareness of the piece as a whole. The result was that I appreciated a greater variety of music to a greater degree. Intrigued by new and unfamiliar sounds, I was less inclined to avoid music whose style wasn’t immediately familiar to me. That being said, I was not able to simply dive into the avant-garde. But I was able to immerse myself in the sound of a lesser-known, more unique composer such as Mahler or Tord Gustavsen.</p>

<p>And at its very core, music is just this — sound. After the last chord of every concert with the Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, my heart raced and my mind marveled at how magnificently the sound reverberated throughout the concert hall — entire seconds of sustained acoustic glory. The audience seemed to be equally mesmerized, remaining silent for a few seconds after the note had died out before applause broke out. A friend of mine went to one such concert and said to me afterwards, “The concert was amazing! Especially that last piece, there was just so much sound coming from all directions.” He had never studied music before and was able to enjoy a classical concert. Most people think jazz and classical music, or any type of non-pop music, are esoteric art forms, inaccessible to those who are untrained and inexperienced. But my near decade of intensive musical training and experience has only made me realize that this isn’t the case. Music is not about mastering the technicalities of a particular genre and being able to play specific notes in a specific style in a specific order. Music is about developing and expressing our natural, human instinct to produce different sounds and appreciate how they interact and combine in beautiful ways.</p>

<p>Later, my new understanding of music changed the way I hear everything around me, not just sounds in the concert hall or the practice room. Being a musician naturally made me more sensitive to any sound at all, and this came at a cost. For instance, when someone on my floor forgets to turn off their alarm and I’m in my room, struggling to write a paper, unable to ignore its constant blaring. Or when on a weekend morning the sound of a dozen high-powered leaf blowers, all humming at a slightly off-tune pitch, wakes me up from my lazy sleep. And try as I might, I simply cannot soundproof my room from the commotion that inevitably fills Old Campus every weekend night: drunken yelling, piercing screeches, blaring music, and senseless whoops. For someone who prefers quiet, being so hearing-sensitive makes Yale a very loud place indeed.</p>

<p>But then again, a heightened awareness of sounds can be refreshing. Now, sitting by an open window during summer nights, I am able to enjoy the concert of crickets — a cacophony during which polyrhythms emerge and evolve through a series of interlocking rhythms and pitches. And I love when the rich and dissonant call of a train echoes through the quietness of the weekday night, each time with a different blend of notes. My walk these days in the woods can be transformed into something memorable when a particularly lyrical bird sings a song. The ability to hear — to really hear — the sounds of the outside world adds a deeper dimension to my experiences. A memory of a trip to New York City would be incomplete without recalling the chaotic urban sounds of car honks, footsteps, and crowded murmuring. A climb to the summit of a mountain would be diminished without noticing the utterly imposing silence.</p>

<p>Learning to hear music as sound taught me how to hear sound as music. After all, music and sound are not separate realms, and neither are the concert hall and the city streets. It is all part of one single sonic environment that our ears inhabit. So the next time you are in the mood for music, try something new; maybe put on Kind of Blue. If you are feeling adventurous the next time you are out and about, try listening to the world as a recording studio full of new and experimental sounds.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>
