<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Essays | Harvey Xia]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//blog/categories/essays/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//"/>
  <updated>2015-07-27T19:24:32-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harvey Xia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harvey@harveyxia.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Aging Memory]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//an-aging-memory"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T13:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//an-aging-memory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My earliest memory is a series of discrete images. A slideshow rather than a scene. The gaps in the pictures obscure what was happening in the memory, leaving me with a collection of words devoid of verbs. There are, however, plenty of nouns and adjectives.</p>

<p>The memory begins with a small, aluminum, semispherical bowl. It was the bowl my grandmother used to feed me with, though if I were being good she would let me attempt it myself — a chopstick in each hand, determined to manipulate the food into my mouth but usually failing. There was something green in the bowl, probably some sort of Chinese vegetable given how much I love vegetables now.</p>

<p>I was in the cramped dining room of my grandparents’ old apartment in Sanming, a dusty industrial place. The bottom of the walls were painted an ugly shade of turquoise, the top half a discolored white. Across one side of the room were big windows that faced the apartment complex’s courtyard. Small potted plants sat on the windowsill. I forget what they looked like.</p>

<p>A soft, yellow light diffused about the room, softening edges and blurring lines, as if turning down the sharpness on a TV. I can’t be sure whether this was how it actually looked, or if my memory has literally faded over time like an old photograph. As I envision the room now, it seems more and more to resemble a sepia print. The memory, the mental image, seems to age as I invoke it. Or perhaps the memory grows clearer, revealing the agedness of the room itself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Journaling and Recordkeeping]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//on-journaling-and-recordkeeping"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//on-journaling-and-recordkeeping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I used to write in my journal all the time in high school, especially between when school ended and when my parents came home. The quietness and boredom of the house brought my inner thoughts into focus. Journaling, then, was my way of managing these thoughts, a way to force the mental torrent into a stream of discrete and lucid ideas.</p>

<p>To maintain a habit of journaling, it seems necessary to have a river of thoughts compelling one to pick up the pen. But the roaring torrent diminishes to a stream when the days get busier. The mind has other tasks to focus on. Responsibilities take precedence over introspection.</p>

<p>As I explored the mountains, valleys, and canyons of Zion, I felt a different tension keeping me from journaling: the desire for a pure and undistracted experience. Journaling, photography, and any other kind of personal recordkeeping place me in the reflective mode. Recordkeeping involves picking and choosing what to jot down, what to take a picture of, requiring that I sift through my immediate memories for the significant ones.</p>

<p>To reflect in this way is to view the present from an elevated perspective, which not only brings me out of the moment’s immediacy, but also transposes my attention from the external world to the internal mind. It seems a shame to dilute the raw and sensory impressions by notebook or camera. There will be time for that later when the day is done.</p>

<p>But at the same time, I want to capture the very experience I’m afraid of diluting, so that I can remember or perhaps even relive it. This internal conflict afflicts writers and those with literary or artistic sensibilities. Does an ideal balance exist between experience and reflection, between the possibilities of living in the moment and reliving the past?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Distractions of College]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//the-distractions-of-college"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T15:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//the-distractions-of-college</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been trying to write a blog post for a few weeks now, but I couldn't seem to follow through with it, for reasons that I'll try my best to articulate. My hope is that trying to put these nebulous feelings into words will help me figure out just what it is that I've been feeling, it seems, more and more intensely since the beginning of college — this unsettling feeling that I'm losing some nameless quality of myself, the value of which I can intuitively sense but can't articulate; an unsettling feeling that colors all of my experiences with the question <em>Does this matter?</em>, and an urgency to do and experience things that, beyond a doubt, have meaning. I realize that all of this sounds very existential. I would agree. But what I'm experiencing can't simply be pigeonholed into the stereotypical "existential crisis." From talking with friends and reading various essays, <sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup> it seems that I'm not the only one struggling with the questions I'm about to raise. (In fact, what inspired me to write this in the first place was an anonymous email that a Yale student sent out commenting on Yale's culture).</p>

<p>Late on a Friday night after an exhausting week, I was determined to write a blog post much like the one I'm attempting now. I wrote the following:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/calvinandhobbes_summer.gif"></p>

<blockquote><blockquote><p>I love this sentiment in <em>Calvin and Hobbes</em>, the idea that in certain moments, the best thing to do is to do nothing at all. Of course, here Calvin and Hobbes aren't literally doing nothing at all; they're sitting back and taking in the beautiful summer day. It makes me think of those perfect summer days where the tree you are sitting under casts a generous shade while the sun above sets the surrounding scenary in the most flattering light. Cool grass between your fingers and toes, gentle winds rustling the leaves. Everything feels, sounds, and looks perfect, invoking a feeling of complete carefree laziness. At its very best, it feels as if you've been transported to a place where your day-to-day worries are so distant that they cease to exist, where being lazy is the virtue.</p>

<p>In the quieter, less hectic moments of my college life, I find myself missing that feeling more and more. At college, my attention is constantly drawn outwards towards classes, activities, internships, and all of that other stuff that American college students are expected to be doing. In high school I suffered through the college application process with the hope that once I got to college, I could focus on learning and making friends and growing. But it doesn't end. I guess this could be the beginning of what they call the "rat race." There's no more time to just be, in the most primitive sense of the word. There's no time to sit in bed and read, to listen to music, or to go for a walk on a nice autumn day. Rather, there is time, but that free time is treated as a luxury too valuable for wasting on "doing nothing."
For the college student, even his leisure time is...</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>I stopped midsentence, choosing instead to numb my mind by browsing Reddit and playing Dota. It wasn't that I didn't want to keep writing, but that it was a Friday night — one of the few times during the week that I get to kickback and give my brain a desperately needed rest after a long week of overclocking it on psets and readings. Leisure writing is, of course, a kind of break from the monotony of school and homework. It's an escape from the restricted, logical, and analytical thinking that my classes require. It's a way to step back from it all — to enter a quiet, isolated, and introspective mode. Writing takes me out of the groundlevel perspective of everyday life to an elevated viewpoint, one that is one step removed from it all, allowing me to think about myself and my life more honestly and deliberately.</p>

<p>Why couldn't I get myself to write more than two paragraphs? Because reflective first-person writing is taxing on the mind in the same way that my classes are. While the reflective me was desperate to have itself heard, the rest of me was simply too tired, not willing to expend effort on anything. I could instead browse reddit while my mind slept. <em>After all,</em> the practical me thought, <em>it's not like I would get any real reward from writing something just for the sake of writing it. Why expend effort on anything that has no return value?</em> But this is just the harmful sort of belief that I've let myself gradually and unconsciously adopt since I've come to Yale. The truth is, reflective self-expression takes an enormous amount of deliberate effort, and moreso, the capacity for insightful thinking diminishes with lack of use. Being constantly preoccupied with classes and extracurriculars and events, I gradually stopped journaling and writing and enjoying  lazy Sunday afternoons. There was always something "more productive" to do.</p>

<p>This is what I've slowly been realizing since college started, that Yale's academic and social culture and my own lack of effort can turn me away from the creative, self-reflective aspect of me. The aspect I think of when I'm asked to describe myself. The part of me I consider as the source of who I am, as my persistent anchor of identity. But "lack of effort" doesn't quite characterize it properly; it's more like my lack of consciously being aware of these external distractions and giving myself more time to reflect. I think this is the root of that unsettling feeling that I'm losing something important of myself; my day to day college life leaves me so tired that I make excuses when I do have time to do some hard thinking by myself.</p>

<p>At college, it seems, everyone's attention is drawn outward and away from themselves, and the culture glorifies this. You're a rockstar if your calendar is filled to the brim with overlapping commitments, your extracurricular activites outnumber your classes, you've secured a prestigious  internship. And the ideal social life is very much analogous to this: you're doing it right if your social nights consist of hopping from one party to the next and on to Toad's, your romantic life (or, sex life, rather) consists of hooking up with various people, especially if others consider them desirable, and then waking up the next morning retelling the events of last night at brunch in the same humorously self-deprecating way that is really just a veil for your own pride that you are, in fact, living up the college life.</p>

<p>And that's that, without a second thought. Brunch ends and you automatically move on to the next set of tasks: completing those homework assignments. And the weeks repeat like this over and over. There's not a moment to spare in between, no time to take a breath and step back from it all. Life is lived passively, reflexively, and robotically from one moment to the next. The mind loses itself in things that seem important but upon examination are really just inflated trivialities. And the effect of college, it seems, is to perpetuate this type of thinking in us, the type that distracts us from considering and pursuing what really matters.</p>

<p>Now, what really matters is of course different for all of us, but I do think that for everyone, what matters comes into focus only through hard and honest thought — thinking in the normative mode, looking for an answer in a domain where it isn't clear whether an answer even exists, let alone what that answer is. It demands the courage to revolt against the values that are given to us and instead exercising one's existentialist agency in defining value where there is none to begin with.</p>

<p>And here is where I find myself getting lost over and over again, feeling discouraged and wondering whether thinking this idealistic nonsense about "what matters" is even worth my precious time. Not to mention, this kind of introspection can be incredibly uncomfortable. Looking at oneself honestly and critically takes a very unique kind of courage that takes time to develop. Reevaluating what I really care about means putting at risk the very principles that I've lived by, and that means admitting the possibility that I've been mistaken. In short, reflecting on one's values and decisions places oneself in a most vulnerable state. Lately I've been asking myself questions like, What does it mean for me to feel shame at getting a low grade despite trying my hardest? Why do I measure myself relative to the academic/professional success of my peers? How come I've known friend X for so long but we never talk about anything beyond what's mundane and humorous?</p>

<p>I'm guessing that many college students never reach the point of uncomfortable self-questioning and unconsciously adopt the values that are most prevalent in their culture. At Yale, these tend to be material values; high grades, an impressive resume, lots of "friends", and a hyperactive social life. After Yale, later in life, what's important will be professional success, reputation, a six-digit salary, and the type of decadent lifestyle that would make any onlooker envious. We've all encountered this type of careerist attitude. And I'm not pretending that I'm totally immune to this attitude either. There does exist a very real necessity in securing financial stability. But the importance of material success is exaggerated. I usually only ever hear mention of the following career paths: becoming a doctor, lawyer, engineer, programmer, banker, and consultant. At dinner parties, when parents ask "What's your major?", they're expecting to hear something like "econ" or "computer science" or "premed". When I say "philosophy," they give me a strange look and they don't know what to say to me.</p>

<p>Usually the response I get to this thought is, "Who are you to judge those who value professional success? You don't know their financial background. They could very well be trying to improve the quality of life for their family." But even in extreme cases my point still holds: valuing material success does not require giving up one's more fundamental values: friendship, family, identity, etc. Material success should only ever be considered as a means to a an end, and never as an end in itself. Spending four years at a place like Yale and then many more years in the job market makes it easy to forget that principle.</p>

<p>Another result of the lack of introspective thinking is that students become unable to talk their values. Granted, sharing one's core values isn't something that we feel comfortable doing with just anybody. It's one thing to refrain from talking about one's deepest beliefs with mere acquaintances;  but what about between friends who have known each other for years? What are two long-time friends to each other if they can't share their thoughts about what they care about? I take it that these sterile, surface-level friendships persist when neither of the two friends take the risk of talking about non-trivial matters that require exposing one's values and emotions. These conversations can be awkward and painful, but with a true friend, they shouldn't be.</p>

<p>I've had the privilege of meeting some incredibly insightful and interesting students during my time here. But always, I find myself wishing that we could talk for longer and about things other than what we're doing over the summer and how our classes are going. I find myself wishing that we were in a culture where it wasn't socially unacceptable to bring up deeper, more personal, perhaps  more depressing issues when they're weighing on either person's mind and to converse honestly about them.</p>

<p>I realize that I can go on for paragraphs and paragraphs, iterating on this point indefinitely, each one digressing a little more from the next but all motivated by the same worries. It's always a challenge for me to package thoughts on this subject into something coherent and elegant. If these questions were that easy to understand, these worries wouldn't be eating away at me all the time.</p>

<p>The most salient point I hoped to articulate was this: creative, self-reflective, introspective thinking is immensely difficult, especially in an environment where my time and energy is nearly depleted by external responsibilities. It takes an additional strength in refusing to let one's environment take away one's capacity for this kind of thinking. Knowing how difficult it is at college, I need to spend more time away from all of the work and noise and distractions. I need to spend more time at the piano, more time reading, taking walks on beautiful fall days, talking to get to know someone, writing for myself; all of it as a way to step back from it all and see how far I've come and where I am headed.</p>

<p>And just as importantly, pursuing experiences to get to know myself and the world. Chasing those experiences that keep alive our innate sensibility to the beauty of the world, a sensibility that dulls with age and with time. Revolting against the incessant demands of practicality as a proud romantic, eyes directed toward the sublime. Because what is it all for if we can no longer dream?</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'><p> <a href="http://www.freewebs.com/lanzbom/EBWhiteLakeEssay.pdf">Once More to the Lake by E.B. White</a> <br> <a href="http://web.ics.purdue.edu/~drkelly/DFWKenyonAddress2005.pdf">Kenyon Commencement Speech by David Foster Wallace</a> <br> <a href="http://www.harveyxia.com/mr-mcculloughs-2012-commencement-speech/">Wellesley High School 2012 Commencement Speech by David McCullough Jr.</a> <br> <a href="http://thoughtcatalog.com/charles-warnke/2011/01/dont-date-a-girl-who-reads/">You Should Date an Illiterate Girl by Charles Warnke</a> <br> <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/09/17/the-referendum/?_r=1">The Referendum by Tim Kreider</a> <br> <a href="http://mitadmissions.org/blogs/entry/meltdown">Meltdown by Lydia K.</a> <br>
<a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></p>
</li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Music as Sound, Sound as Music]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//music-as-sound-sound-as-music"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//music-as-sound-sound-as-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Leaning forward in my chair, I gripped my saxophone in anticipation. It was my first rehearsal with the Senior Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, the first musical group to ever intimidate me with its degree of talent and level of perfection. Widely regarded as one of the top wind ensembles in the world, the group is led by Michael Mucci — a conductor, educator, and mentor whom I admire deeply. During his opening remarks he said a curious thing.</p>

<p>“You are all here because you love sound.”</p>

<p>Strange, I thought. Why would he use the word sound? In my mind, the word “sound” stood uncomfortable close to “noise.” I wasn’t just producing mere sounds; I was making music — an art that requires skill and refinement, an art that is the opposite of noise. But for some reason, his words remained in the back of my mind and their meaning grew clearer as I matured musically through my high school years. Before this, however, I had to learn that listening to music is just as much a craft as making music.I didn’t always know how to listen to music well, and I still have a lot to learn. I remember how teachers would recommend that I listen to recordings like Miles Davis’ Kind of Blue and John Coltrane’s A Love Supreme, and how I would get bored after a few minutes. I thought it was because I didn’t understand the music theory underlying the jazz. But after devoting much time to learning about chord progressions and two-fives and secondary dominants, I still could not enjoy these records. Understanding that the tune “So What” has a modal structure that modulates up a half step in the bridge did not help me at all in appreciating the track.</p>

<p>Eventually, I was introduced to the concept of tone. Teachers emphasized the importance of developing a unique sound, asking me questions like “How would you describe your sound?” Dark, rounded, and pure, I would say. I knew that good tone was an important aspect of musicianship, but I hadn’t thought about it as something up to the musician to define. Miles Davis was always championed as having the quintessentially unique voice, so I began paying more attention to the way his trumpet sounded, not just the notes he played. With this attitude of listening for how things sounded holistically rather than how the notes were arranged, I gave Kind of Blue another shot. This time, I found myself able to sit through the full nine minutes of each track with a sustained interest. Instead of fixating on that particular bluesy lick that Cannonball played or the pentatonic scale that Coltrane used, I focused on how the richness of Bill Evan’s chords complemented Miles’ subdued tone. I noticed the contrast between the distinct sounds of Coltrane, Cannonball, and Miles, and how that lent the album a mosaic-like quality. I absorbed the recording’s general chilled, quiet, impressionistic ethos. I could go on about what I love about the album, but the point is that a simple shift in my listener’s attitude was all that I needed to understand the music. Studying jazz theory was unnecessary because listening to music involves something much more fundamental — it involves the skill of listening to sound.</p>

<p>I approached both new and familiar pieces of music with this new philosophy, asking the question: What kinds of sounds are these artists attempting to create? Sound, of course, gets conveyed in many different forms. In jazz, for example, the artist’s phrasing, tone, dynamics, intonation, rhythmic and melodic choices all characterize his sound. In classical, the composer’s orchestration and compositional choices as well as the performer’s interpretive choices comprise the sound. With this attitude, I listened with more focus; with more attention to subtle nuances and with more awareness of the piece as a whole. The result was that I appreciated a greater variety of music to a greater degree. Intrigued by new and unfamiliar sounds, I was less inclined to avoid music whose style wasn’t immediately familiar to me. That being said, I was not able to simply dive into the avant-garde. But I was able to immerse myself in the sound of a lesser-known, more unique composer such as Mahler or Tord Gustavsen.</p>

<p>And at its very core, music is just this — sound. After the last chord of every concert with the Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, my heart raced and my mind marveled at how magnificently the sound reverberated throughout the concert hall — entire seconds of sustained acoustic glory. The audience seemed to be equally mesmerized, remaining silent for a few seconds after the note had died out before applause broke out. A friend of mine went to one such concert and said to me afterwards, “The concert was amazing! Especially that last piece, there was just so much sound coming from all directions.” He had never studied music before and was able to enjoy a classical concert. Most people think jazz and classical music, or any type of non-pop music, are esoteric art forms, inaccessible to those who are untrained and inexperienced. But my near decade of intensive musical training and experience has only made me realize that this isn’t the case. Music is not about mastering the technicalities of a particular genre and being able to play specific notes in a specific style in a specific order. Music is about developing and expressing our natural, human instinct to produce different sounds and appreciate how they interact and combine in beautiful ways.</p>

<p>Later, my new understanding of music changed the way I hear everything around me, not just sounds in the concert hall or the practice room. Being a musician naturally made me more sensitive to any sound at all, and this came at a cost. For instance, when someone on my floor forgets to turn off their alarm and I’m in my room, struggling to write a paper, unable to ignore its constant blaring. Or when on a weekend morning the sound of a dozen high-powered leaf blowers, all humming at a slightly off-tune pitch, wakes me up from my lazy sleep. And try as I might, I simply cannot soundproof my room from the commotion that inevitably fills Old Campus every weekend night: drunken yelling, piercing screeches, blaring music, and senseless whoops. For someone who prefers quiet, being so hearing-sensitive makes Yale a very loud place indeed.</p>

<p>But then again, a heightened awareness of sounds can be refreshing. Now, sitting by an open window during summer nights, I am able to enjoy the concert of crickets — a cacophony during which polyrhythms emerge and evolve through a series of interlocking rhythms and pitches. And I love when the rich and dissonant call of a train echoes through the quietness of the weekday night, each time with a different blend of notes. My walk these days in the woods can be transformed into something memorable when a particularly lyrical bird sings a song. The ability to hear — to really hear — the sounds of the outside world adds a deeper dimension to my experiences. A memory of a trip to New York City would be incomplete without recalling the chaotic urban sounds of car honks, footsteps, and crowded murmuring. A climb to the summit of a mountain would be diminished without noticing the utterly imposing silence.</p>

<p>Learning to hear music as sound taught me how to hear sound as music. After all, music and sound are not separate realms, and neither are the concert hall and the city streets. It is all part of one single sonic environment that our ears inhabit. So the next time you are in the mood for music, try something new; maybe put on Kind of Blue. If you are feeling adventurous the next time you are out and about, try listening to the world as a recording studio full of new and experimental sounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Look at Snow]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//how-to-look-at-snow"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//how-to-look-at-snow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>This piece is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lipogram">lipogram</a> in which I did not use the letter E (do a Ctrl-F if you don’t believe me). It was immensely challenging, but I had a fun time writing it. Enjoy.</em></p>

<p> 
Nothing can approach that first sighting of snow falling softly from a calm gray sky. Racing to my window and taking a good long look, visions of snowballs and toboggans and igloos flash through my mind. I am struck by a familiar youthful thrill. But I also think of walking through snowy woods. So I grab my stuff and go out.</p>

<p>Road lamps cast a glow, gold light diffusing warmly against a dark bluish background. Distant things sound faint. My boots crunch. Pausing, I pick up a soft but distinct sound, hard to put into words. Possibly how a thousand tiny crystal shards would sound colliding — a soothing, glassy tingling, akin to rhythmic rain. Withdrawn into isolation, I walk, not minding how cold it is. Soon, though, it turns into a raging blizzard of furious winds and blinding snow. I hurry back and as I rush in, I am struck by a familiar air: an aroma of smoky wood, a crackling of burning logs. Only during a snowstorm is this so inviting. A cup of hot cocoa awaits and I top it off with big marshmallows.</p>

<p>Sipping, I watch as snow’s sublimity transforms my world; all physical flaws vanish — no footprints, no sign of dirt; only a minimalistic fantasy. A blank canvas, full of possibility. And this, I think, is how all should look at snow.</p>

<p>But most don’t look at it this way. To many, snow is that awful stuff that sticks to scarfs and hats and hair, that stings skin, that drifts and blows around annoyingly; a cold dust that afflicts us in months around January. Moms and dads and various adults moan about how snow ruins roads, forming hazardous traps that all of us must unavoidably confront. Driving to work or school, typically quotidian, turns into an awful affair — traffic, plow trucks, and a slurry of salt, slush, and snow. Catching such words, I always think, <em>How sad, to think if that’s all snow is.</em> Having grown up in a Boston suburb, I’m fairly familiar with all things having to do with snow. Snow practically accounts for half of my childhood joy, a joy that I will not outgrow. So, naturally, I think that a man who knows only how to complain about snow is dogmatic and lacks a youthful outlook that savors snow for its fun and its bright and shining charm. Such a man is missing out on what’s important about snow — its magic. And that day that my school was caught amidst an abrupt snowstorm was nothing short of magical.</p>

<p>What a vivid sight — gothic archways, courtyards normally grassy, and old oaks showcasing a grand snowy cap. At midnight, vast crowds flock to Old Campus, lit by lamplight. Small groups form and soon, total chaos bursts out. A thousand kids frolic in snow on a Monday night, choosing fun and punting work. Snowballs fly this way and that. Occasionally, amidst raucous laughs and joyous shouts, a satisfying thud sounds; a good shot found its mark.</p>

<p>Panting, I go back to my dorm, worn out by our wintry fight. Collapsing on my chair, blood still pumping fast, I look out of my window, gazing out at snow dancing around a lamplight’s halo. I am calm again, happy, and I think: <em>Thank god for snow.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
