<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cooking | Harvey Xia]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//blog/categories/cooking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//"/>
  <updated>2015-01-18T15:17:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harvey Xia]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harvey@harveyxia.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not-so-instant ramen]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//not-so-instant-ramen"/>
    <updated>2013-07-15T18:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//not-so-instant-ramen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until a few weeks ago, I thought that 'ramen' referred only to that packaged stuff notorious for sustaining students through their college years. I had no idea that 'instant ramen' was based off of a real Japanese dish. A friend told me about a small, locally famous ramen shop in Porter Square, Cambridge. "Give yourself some time", she said. "You'll be waiting in line for a while."</p>

<p>Turns out there are two ramen shops in Porter Square, both of which are regarded as the best ramen in the Boston area. The one my friend was referring to is called "Yume Wo Katare." The one I ended up going to is called "Sapporo Ramen." Yume Wo Katare is closed over the summer. I guess its Japanese chef, who apparently has opened multiple restaurants in Japan, is visiting Japan.</p>

<p>Sapporo Ramen is a charming little shop hidden away in a small shopping center. It's the size of a living room, and it's tiny kitchen is tucked away in a corner. There are only about 7 or 8 tables, and a line usually stretches down the hallway. I have always been a big fan of instant ramen, especially the fiery Korean Shin brand. I was blown away by my first real bowl of ramen, served in a large clay bowl, filled to the brim with yellow noodles and steaming broth. Ramen looks very attractive when served with all its toppings laid out nicely. I told myself to remember to snap a picture before I dug in, but my appetite got the better of me. Caitlin reminded me, but it was too late.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/not-so-instant_ramen/sapporo_ramen.jpg" title="'Before I ate it all'" ></p>

<p>The broth, brewed with pork bones and aromatics for over 10 hours, tastes amazing — a savory and salty umami heaven. The yellow wheat noodles are what the name 'ramen' refers to. They are made using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramen#Noodles">kansui</a>, a mix of sodium carbonate and potassium carbonate. The alkalinity of these two compounds keeps the noodles from becoming mushy when sitting in the hot broth and helps them maintain the chewiness that makes them so satisfying to munch on. On top of the broth and ramen, a number of toppings are placed. This <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramen#Regional_variations">depends on the style</a>. The noodles I ordered had pork, beansprouts, scallions, nori (dried seaweed), corn, and half a boied egg.</p>

<p>The ramen was so good I finished the whole bowl, including the soup. I felt bloated afterwards, but it was worth it. During another visit I ordered double the amount of noodles and finished all of it, plus the broth, plus Caitlin's broth. Again, worth it. Besides, it's customary in Japanese culture to finish everything on your plate.</p>

<p>We were so impressed by these noodles that Caitlin and I decided to try our hand at them. I followed this <a href="http://norecipes.com/blog/tonkotsu-ramen-recipe/#sthash.ffFEVWKz.00fOSJvo.dpbs">recipe</a>, which I highly recommend if you want to try making ramen from scratch. The recipe is for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramen#Soup">tonkotsu</a> style ramen, characterized by its creamy, fat and collagen rich pork broth. The author even has a recipe for making your own ramen noodles from scratch.</p>

<p>I have to say, making the two bowls of ramen was one of the more challenging and stressful things I've done. The broth itself took three hours to prepare and involved cleaning the bones and purifying the blood from them. We used a pressure cooker to speed up the process of extracting that yummy umami flavor from the bones. The chasu required about an hour of slow simmering in a rich braising liquid (miso, soy sauce, sake, mirin, cinnamon bark, star anise, sugar, etc.) In fact, most of the sauces required were ridiculously complicated, requiring a vast number of ingredients, most of which I had never heard of before. I guess that's where the uniquely memorable flavor comes from.</p>

<p>Preparing it required a lot of attention, multitasking, and care. The details mattered, from mincing the fatback small enough that it would dissolve properly (giving the broth an added creaminess) to slicing the scallions in the right shape.</p>

<p>After two days of preparation, it was pretty satisfying to see the finished bowls.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/not-so-instant_ramen/homemade_ramen.jpg" title="'One of the greatest achievements to date'" ></p>

<p>Attention to the details is what defines great ramen, and from experience, I can say that this dish has a very high skill cap. What I mean by that is that unlike some foods (making toast, for instance), ramen can vary greatly in its quality — from great to legendary. It's also a dish that gives the chef lots of space for innovation, both in preparation method and choice of ingredients. There are so many styles of ramen out there, and each shop has its own signature variations that define the dish.</p>

<p>I plan on traveling to Japan in the not-too-distant-future to experience first-hand its culture, history, and its world-renowned food. Hopefully it's not too naive of me to work towards perfecting a ramen that someday I'll get to call my own. This is the beginning of my story of ramen. May it unfold one slurp at a time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning to cook for an epicurean]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.harveyxia.com//learning-to-cook-for-an-epicurean"/>
    <updated>2013-07-01T17:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.harveyxia.com//learning-to-cook-for-an-epicurean</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>"The flesh receives as unlimited the limits of pleasure; and to provide it requires unlimited time. But the mind, intellectually grasping what the end and limit of the flesh is, and banishing the terrors of the future, procures a complete and perfect life, and we have no longer any need of unlimited time. Nevertheless the mind does not shun pleasure, and even when circumstances make death imminent, the mind does not lack enjoyment of the best life."</p>

<p>— Epicurus, Principle Doctrines—</p></blockquote>

<p>I was confused when I first heard the term "epicurean" used to describe someone who pursues sensual pleasures (especially with respect to food). There is the common misconcenption that the ancient Epicureans, since they believed that pleasure is the chief Good, advocated pursuing pleasure without limitation. Epicurus actually considered freedom from fear and pain as the optimum state. This required the individual to exercise prudence and restraint, because enjoying too much of a good thing can decrease satisfaction and increase desire. So how come the name of a philosophical doctrine that preaches moderation and condemns excess is used to describe those who love gourmet food? But before I offer my thoughts on this, I'll first talk about my new hobby.</p>

<p>I've always been curious about cooking from a distance; on cooking shows, I would admire chefs like Gordon Ramsay and Ming Tsai artfully construct a dish whose appearance would be enough to make my mouth water. And naturally, I'm fan of good food, everything from those perfectly cooked Five Guys burgers to the amazingly authentic food of Sichuan Gourmet.</p>

<p>Only recently though, have I resolved to learn how to cook, how to <em>really</em> cook, adding it to my lifelong TODO list. Why now? I think partly it's because during the semester I very quickly get bored of eating college food. It's not that the food tastes bad (Yale serves great college food except for that nasty cauliflower overcooked to a paste that Berkeley sometimes makes), but that it tastes boring. After a few weeks everything tastes familiar, and not in the good homey way. It tastes familiar in the I'm-tired-of-this-same-old-shit sort of way.</p>

<p>Another reason is my lifelong obsession with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szechuan_cuisine">Sichuan gourmet</a>. Sichuan is a region in China famous for it's ridiculously spicy-hot, flavor-packed dishes. I haven't experienced any other type of food that matches Sichuan cuisine in terms of sheer flavor and uniqueness of taste. No other food can make me down so much rice in one meal.</p>

<p>Also, in the past year I've been going out to restaurants more often, sometimes to upscale places. I find myself having stronger, more polarized opinions about the food. Sometimes I will be so impressed with the food that I won't be able to stop thinking about it, like having a song get stuck in your head. Sometimes I'll be so severely disappointed with the food that I'll publicly swear never to go to that restaurant again.</p>

<p>This summer I will try my inexperienced hand at the world's various cuisines, starting with the dishes that I love. Every so often I'll write about my successes, my failures, and what I've learned about the nature of taste. I'm determined to learn all the basic cooking techniques (sauteing, baking, boiling, etc), <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RjWkO9A-Ckk">how to wield a knife</a>, and how to use different ingredients. Hopefully I will also learn a thing or two about enjoying food that is prepared with such great care.</p>

<p>Viewed in this way, the Epicurean label isn't as paradoxical as I originally thought. Fully appreciating food for its excellence isn't as easy or instinctive as I thought. Perhaps the Epicurean would say that thoughtfully enjoying the gastronomic goodness of food is far more in the Epicurean spirit than simply gobbling it down to satiate hunger.</p>

<p>Eating can be as much an art as cooking, and cooking, I imagine, enlightens one to this art.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
